<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.3/JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en-US" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="original-article" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HSAH</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Hertziana Studies in Art History</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title>HSAH</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn/>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Bibliotheca Hertziana - Max Planck Institute for Art
                    History</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.48431/hsah.0108</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel">
                    <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The Description of Places in Biondo’s Italia
                    Illustrata</article-title>
                <alt-title>Places in Italia Illustrata</alt-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" deceased="no" id="bajifhiaeb">
                    <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid"
                        >https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5629-0981</contrib-id>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Richter</surname>
                        <given-names>Kai-Florian</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <email>kai-florian.richter@umu.se</email>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="affjbjfdiejifi"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="affjbjfdiejifi"><institution content-type="orgname">Department of Computing
                        Science</institution><institution content-type="orgdiv1">Umea
                        Universitet</institution><addr-line/><city>Umea</city><country>Sweden</country></aff>
            </contrib-group>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>31</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2022</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <elocation-id>8</elocation-id>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>28</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>28</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2020</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>This material is distributed under the terms of the Creative
                    Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
                    reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
                    cited.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Bibliotheca Hertziana - Max Planck Institute for Art
                    History</copyright-holder>
                <license license-type="open-access"
                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                    <license-p>This work is licensed under Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                        International (CC BY 4.0).</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <p id="e8iwdj1az3aq">This chapter outlines a quantitative method for analyzing
                    location descriptions. Generally, such a quantitative analysis allows for
                    identifying predominant features of these descriptions and, given a sufficiently
                    large corpus, may allow for statistical inferences. Here, an English translation
                    of Biondo’s chapter on the region Latium is used as a small case study
                    illustrating the method. The analyzed features include the frequency
                    (distribution) of the level of granularity of those entities referred to in the
                    descriptions, which spatial hierarchical structures emerge from referring to
                    different entities on potentially different levels of granularity and the
                    frequency of these structures, and which spatial relationships between entities
                    dominate in the descriptions. The chapter presents results of this analysis and
                    discusses them in detail, also pointing out limitations of the method. However,
                    mainly the chapter is to be read as an introduction to this particular analysis
                    approach, which may be used to complement other analyses and may offer insights
                    not otherwise gained.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
                <kwd>place descriptions</kwd>
                <kwd>hierarchical structures</kwd>
                <kwd>spatial relations</kwd>
                <kwd>spatial cognition</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="import-yxhmhouhjy" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>1. Introduction</title>
            <p id="u4ew0sxx3qcq">Place descriptions<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref> answer a
                ‘where question’ about a thing or event – they localize the thing or event in a
                larger space, such that the recipients of the description understand where it is
                relative to that larger space. Place descriptions are natural language expressions,
                in that they provide great flexibility in how they might be constructed, which to a
                large extent depends on the communication context. Generally, however, they take the
                following form to describe the location of some thing or event:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="zpv68lgd7egk">[[(opt) subject verb] (opt) preposition] NP<xref ref-type="fn"
                        rid="fn2">2</xref></p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="pzg3ovsvqo8q">Here, “NP” represents the noun phrase referring to a location
                (e.g., “Rome”). The location can be further specified using an (optional)
                preposition (e.g., “in Rome”, “near Rome”), and might be (optionally) embedded in a
                complete sentence (e.g., “The Pantheon is in Rome” or “He lives near Rome”).</p>
            <p id="wbi1lwu0illr">The scale or granularity<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref> of
                the spatial entities referred to in such place descriptions can vary greatly,
                ranging from objects on table-top spaces (e.g., “the book is on the left of the
                desk”), to locating countries (e.g., “Italy is in Europe”). Independent of the level
                of granularity, these descriptions typically exhibit a hierarchical structure in
                their granularity, i.e., the different entities mentioned in the description differ
                in their respective level of granularity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>
                Often, these structures can appear as zooming in (e.g., “in Rome, at the Colosseum”)
                or as zooming out (e.g., “at the Colosseum in Rome”); whereby they move from a
                location on a coarser granularity level (“Rome”) to one on a finer level (“the
                Colosseum”) or vice versa.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref> These hierarchical
                structures reflect the hierarchical organization of spatial knowledge in our
                    mind.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="kfux9aw9vxmg">6</xref> They also capture the
                relationship between figure and ground, i.e., the fact that these descriptions are
                referring expressions that relate some foregrounded entity (the
                    <italic>figure</italic>) as relative to another (the <italic>ground</italic>).
                (The former is typically seen to be more movable, smaller, geometrically simpler,
                more salient, and/or more recent than the latter).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7"
                    >7</xref> In other words, the ground entity acts as a reference object for the
                figure. In verbal communication, addressers usually choose reference objects of
                which they assume that their characteristics (e.g., name or location) are known to
                the recipients of the description and, thus, help to resolve ambiguity and
                uncertainty in locating the entity referred to.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="svmht4we0wzt">8</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-lynpo3pspv" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>2. Aims</title>
            <p id="fakvo4exp7c">In a nutshell, the aim of this chapter is to illustrate an approach
                to analyzing location descriptions using quantitative measures. Such a quantitative
                analysis will allow for identifying predominant features of these descriptions and,
                given a sufficiently large corpus, may allow for statistical inferences. The
                analyzed features include the frequency (distribution) of the level of granularity
                of those entities referred to in the descriptions, which hierarchical structure
                appears most frequently, and which spatial relationships between entities dominate
                in the descriptions. Such quantitative data then in turn allows us to draw
                conclusions about stylistic preferences in describing locations. More interestingly,
                it also tells us something about the underlying spatial knowledge and
                conceptualization of space (the <italic>mental</italic> image) of those providing
                the descriptions, but also the assumed (background) knowledge and level of
                familiarity of the addressee.</p>
            <p id="hyuc2hkvcjeg">The analysis approach will be demonstrated using a chapter of
                Biondo’s <italic>Italia Illustrata</italic> as the sample corpus,<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="czm2px93xu9p">9</xref> but it can, in principle, be applied to any
                collection of verbal or textual location descriptions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10"
                    >10</xref> The approach was originally developed for analyzing verbal
                descriptions collected through a location-based game that asked participants to
                respond to the prompt, “Tell me where you are.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11"
                    >11</xref> Hence, using it on a different corpus may require some adaptations in
                practice, as explained in the Methods section below.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-w80oht57vl" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>3. Methods</title>
            <p id="mgc0q15i3a4">Generally, in performing the analysis outlined above, the corpus at
                hand is first divided into individual statements (expressions or parts of
                speech/text). These can be individual location descriptions if the corpus is a
                collection of descriptions made by multiple people, or individual sentences, or even
                parts of sentences if the corpus covers a text by a single author. In the next step,
                each statement is annotated with respect to levels of granularity, its hierarchical
                structure, and the spatial relationships between the entities mentioned. Counting
                these annotations results in some frequency distributions for each of the aspects,
                which can then be further analyzed.</p>
            <p id="qooza58un1t">For the case study presented here, an English translation of a
                chapter of Biondo’s <italic>Italia Illustrata</italic><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12"
                    >12</xref> was chosen to illustrate this kind of analysis. Biondo’s chapter
                describes the region of Latium – the region Rome is located in. As stated above, the
                analysis is executed on the basis of individual units, i.e., statement by statement.
                Therefore, the text needs to be split into these statements first, which requires a
                mix of automated and manual processing of the document.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn13">13</xref> It is important to note that for the corpus at hand –
                Biondo’s chapter – a statement is not the same as a sentence in a grammatical sense,
                but is rather a semantic unit (or construction) that forms a self-contained
                description. Accordingly, splitting the text is more elaborate than simply looking
                at each individual sentence, as is explained in the following.</p>
            <p id="ev4j4kyvol2">The chosen chapter from Biondo’s book contains 432 sentences
                overall, i.e., statements finished by a full stop. The full stop character (“.”) was
                used to automatically split the document into individual elements for further
                processing. From here, all following steps in the analysis were performed
                ‘manually’, i.e., via manual annotations and coding done by the researcher. This was
                deemed necessary as these steps require semantic decisions that are difficult to
                automatize – without however excluding the fact that automatization would, in
                principle, be possible for some of these steps (see the discussion below).</p>
            <p id="odk1a7nle27n">In a initial run-through of the separated sentences, it was first
                decided whether each sentence contained (elements of) a place description at all.
                This first run-through eliminated 201 sentences, leaving 231 for analysis. However,
                several of these 231 sentences de facto combine several statements conjoined by
                conjunctions, such as “and” or “although”, or punctuation marks, such as a colon
                (“:”) or semicolon (“;”). Accordingly, these sentences were in turn split into their
                respective sub-statements, resulting in a final sum of 271 statements culled for
                    analysis.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref></p>
            <p id="xviwlluzd8ma">Next, in the annotation step every statement was categorized
                according to whether it was a ‘proper place description’ or rather designation,
                described some movement of people (individuals or groups), animals, or objects
                through space, or described an event located at some place. A proper place
                description describes a geographic location in the strict sense of ‘place
                description’ as explained in the introduction. Examples of such proper place
                descriptions or designations are sentences 28 and 170 of the Biondo chapter:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="nx6xqdlcih5">28: There was in the forum of the Antiates a temple of Castor
                    and Pollux, whom they called their Saviours according to Strabo.</p>
                <p id="gmt5nspb37b">170: Above the town of Traiectum, three miles from the sea,
                    beside the Liris, is the castle of Speninum.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="u6yngnhbcqee">The former locates a temple with respect to a forum, the latter
                locates the castle of Speninum with respect to the town of Traiectum, the sea, and
                the (river) Liris.</p>
            <p id="ztk3ffuwb79b">Some statements rather describe a trajectory, i.e., a physical or
                virtual motion event, of somebody or something moving through space, describing that
                space along the way. An example of such a ‘movement statement’ is sentence 110:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="vkra6fuajbp8">Four cohorts were dispatched with C. Servilius Ahala by a
                    circuitous route, and, having captured the hill overhanging the city, from their
                    higher position where there was no defence, they invaded the walls with an
                    enormous noise and shouting.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="jokrpkcozz8">While these statements contain elements of place descriptions, for
                example, locating the hill with respect to the city, they do so ‘implicitly’ and in
                passing, i.e., at least from the outset their main aim is to describe some motion
                event.</p>
            <p id="p0hq15eihtsu">Other statements describe (historical) events that happened at
                specific locations, thereby introducing or describing these locations. Again, these
                contain elements of place descriptions as defined above, but the purpose seems
                rather to provide some historical context for these locations. An example of such a
                statement is sentence 140:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="letx1gsyrscm">But although the gulf of Caieta and the citadel were of great
                    and ancient fame, it was not a city until the Saracens (as we have shown above)
                    destroyed Formiae.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="aneueysmo1u">Following the annotation step, each statement was analyzed with
                respect to the granularity – or scale – of each geographic entity referenced in the
                statement, following the approach by Richter et al.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="qy7p91jfxjyl">15</xref> The different levels of granularity employed and
                some example entities for each level are listed in <xref ref-type="table"
                    rid="ztwu0su0i5ka">Table 1</xref> below. The original classification scheme of
                granularity levels as developed by Richter et al. has been extended for the analysis
                presented here. In their work, <xref ref-type="bibr"
                    rid="Richter.2013c">(Richter D./Winter et al. 2013)</xref> and <xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013b">(Richter D./Vasardani et al. 2013)</xref>
                looked at location descriptions that would localize a person relative to their
                environment (they asked people to “Tell us where you are”).<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn16">16</xref> As the geographic footprint of a person is rather small,
                differentiating geographic entities beyond city scale was not deemed relevant in
                their analysis. However, in the case of Biondo’s description of Italy and its
                regions, it quickly turned out that towns and cities are the main geographic
                entities that are being localized. To account for this crucial difference, the
                original classification scheme was extended, introducing a finer differentiation on
                coarser levels of granularity, as is indicated in <xref ref-type="table"
                    rid="ztwu0su0i5ka">Table 1</xref>.</p>
            <p id="py9xlfbkpevi">At the same time, hierarchical structures present in the
                descriptions were identified (e.g., ‘zooming in’, ‘zooming out’). Following Richter
                et al.,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="zx35zsz0d8bh">17</xref> a location description can
                exhibit the following hierarchical structures:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                    <p id="wt4pdhvp1p2t">Strictly hierarchical: a location description shows a
                        behavior of strictly monotonically increasing or decreasing granularity
                        levels. The sequence of levels is either zooming in or zooming out. There
                        are no duplicates on the same level of granularity.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p id="vlv52hpguc5k">Partially hierarchical: a location description shows a
                        monotonically increasing or decreasing behavior. Duplicates on the same
                        level occur.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p id="n2c12evxv1dg">Flat: all entities referred to in a location description
                        are on the same level of granularity.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p id="tn55sy5zxtd">Unordered: non-monotonic location descriptions, i.e., the
                        description shows first (partial) zooming in and then (partial) zooming out
                        behavior or vice versa.</p>
                </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="ztwu0su0i5ka">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>The different levels of granularity employed in the analysis</title>
                </caption>
                <table id="tbl-meyw6nltdgev" frame="box" rules="all" cellpadding="5">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>level of granularity</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>description</p></th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>furniture</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>location within a room (“at my desk”,
                                    “bed”), small vehicles (“bike”), or small natural features (“a
                                    stone”)</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>room</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>location within a building, or within
                                    parts belonging to it, medium-sized vehicle</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>building</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>location of a building, large
                                    vehicles</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>street</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>streets within a town, larger than
                                    building and/or vaguer boundaries than building, includes
                                    infrastructure and public spaces, natural features of medium
                                    size</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>district</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>suburb, rural district, post-code
                                    areas</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>city</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>town or city, metropolitan areas</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>geographic feature</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>major roads between towns, single
                                    mountains</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>region</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>named parts of a country, mountain
                                    ranges</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>country</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>countries, seas, oceans</p></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p id="t7ffb0xiyhia">Further, for the proper place descriptions, an analysis of the
                spatial relationships between the geographic entities mentioned in a statement was
                performed, using the categories detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="ptr5s9qtqt9"
                    >Table 2</xref> and again following the approach by Richter et al.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="sc1h6ueh55xl">18</xref> Most often, prepositions indicate the
                kind of spatial relationship that exists between two entities.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn19">19</xref> Importantly, a statement can reflect several of these
                relationships at the same time as, for instance, a given entity can be localized
                using both qualitative and quantitative distances to other entities. For example,
                sentence 106 (“And Strabo reports that the land reclaimed from the marshes, from the
                Pontine Marshes to the territory of Terracina, stretched for a hundred stades, which
                our contemporaries calculate at eight miles”) says that “the land” stretches between
                some marshes and a territory (qualitative distance), which covers a distance of a
                hundred stades (quantitative distance). In addition to the categories used by
                Richter et al. a further category – “correspondence” – is introduced to capture
                occurrences when Biondo links historical (Roman or earlier) place names, which are
                no longer in use, to the (then)-current place name of an entity (e.g., sentence 11:
                “In order to follow the most knowledgeable author in antiquity and also Plinius […],
                we are compelled to attach the region of the Latins to our present-day region
                Campania and Maritima”).</p>
            <p id="g4tt34lqnczq">Spatial relationships were not investigated for statements
                describing movement or events since, for one, their main purpose is not to localize
                entities with respect to each other as explained above, and, for another, an initial
                attempt at this analysis showed that many of these statements are not
                easily/unambiguously categorizable (if at all).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20"
                    >20</xref></p>
            <table-wrap id="ptr5s9qtqt9">
                <label>Table 2.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Categories of spatial relationships used in the analysis</title>
                </caption>
                <table id="tbl-x5ngidkf7yo" frame="box" rules="all" cellpadding="5">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>spatial relation</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>indicators (prepositions)</p></th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>topology</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>along, in, on, outside, through, up
                                …</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>relative orientation</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>across, in front of, opposite, under
                                    …</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>qualitative distance</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>by, close to, just off, near, next to
                                    …</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>quantitative distance</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>it is <italic>n</italic> miles,
                                        <italic>n</italic> miles from …</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>correspondence</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>by the name, was then, which is now,
                                    changed to …</p></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p id="v6nusd9rv15d">Once the annotation of the statements is finished, different
                quantitative indicators can be calculated, which are explained in the next
                section.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-pjjw4qi9ch" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>4. Results</title>
            <p id="t90thacaxf6c">From the small corpus of 271 analyzed statements (constructions or
                collocations), 195 were categorized as a proper place description, 24 as movement
                statements, and 52 as events. In other words, the purpose of the majority of
                statements (72 percent) is to localize geographic entities, while a smaller part
                (8.9 percent and 19.1 percent, respectively) refer to (motion) events – with the
                caveat that 201 sentences (46.5 percent) of the chapter’s overall sentences had been
                excluded from analysis in the initial step, i.e., did not contain (useful) spatial
                references at all.</p>
            <p id="arxsm3ypm5is">Overall, the 271 statements mention 589 geographic entities, or
                just over two entities per statement on average. These entities are not necessarily
                unique, since several (consecutive) statements may refer to the same entity; or an
                entity might be mentioned more than once in a single statement, for that
                    matter.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref> It is interesting to note that
                while on average there are overall just over two entities mentioned in a statement
                (m = 2.17), for movement statements the average is slightly higher (m = 2.54), while
                for event statements it is on average less than two (m = 1.77).</p>
            <p id="qtxgp3jiwrcr"><xref ref-type="table" rid="zh5n8vh19kzh">Table 3</xref> provides
                details on the levels of granularity these entities fall on, both overall and for
                the different types of statements. It can be observed that most references are made
                to entities on the city level (i.e., mentions of towns and cities), followed by
                entities on the geographic features level (e.g., rivers, major roads, or forests).
                Given the purpose of Biondo’s text, namely describing the geography of Italy and its
                regions, this finding may not be surprising.</p>
            <table-wrap id="zh5n8vh19kzh">
                <label>Table 3.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Frequency distribution of the levels of granularity</title>
                </caption>
                <table id="tbl-mq5w7luj87s" frame="box" rules="all" cellpadding="5">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>furniture</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>room</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>building</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>street</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>district</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>city</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>geog. features</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>region</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>country</p></th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>all</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9(1.53%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11(1.87%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>57(9.68%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>26(4.41%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>48(8.15%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>212(36.00%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>137(23.26%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>74(12.56%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>15(2.55%)</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>proper place description</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5(1.15%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8(1.84%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>46(10.55%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12(2.75%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>33(7.57%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>152(34.86%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>114(26.15%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>57(13.07%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9(2.06%)</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>movement</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0(0.00%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="t1c1oiqlugp5">0</p><p
                                    id="s6p6e1wgysc">(0.00%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="i6r14i2irx14">3</p><p
                                    id="jledo8s1uas">(4.92%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>9(14.75%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="vppx9g0lqzc8">8</p><p
                                    id="aym9pyp3yzj">(13.12%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="i45q0lqhyprp">22</p><p
                                    id="hsbpk1w7d3u">(36.07%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11(18.03%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7(11.48%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="lw5jqajtajjd">1</p><p
                                    id="pzzgq49k8ndn">(1.64%)</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>events</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4(4.35%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="in0vae28fier">3</p><p
                                    id="o0w1ma85o0o99">(3.26%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8(8.70%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5(5.44%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7(7.61%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>38(41.30%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="iz7ilajwnn1o">12</p><p
                                    id="ploysctjvugf">(13.04%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10(10.87%)</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5(5.44%)</p></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p id="mdncyc3jy1kw"><xref ref-type="table" rid="mah9dpmvtk3o">Table 4</xref> lists which
                hierarchical structures are contained in the different statements. No clear image
                seems to emerge here, except that by looking at all statements, irrespective of
                their type, no clear hierarchical structure is observable. Descriptions are either
                ‘flat’ or ‘unordered’ (63 and 81 out of 271, respectively; or 23 percent and 30
                percent of all descriptions respectively). The rest of the statements either
                (partially) zoom in or (partially) zoom out, with approximately equal distribution.
                The same holds true when only looking at proper place descriptions. A different
                image emerges when looking at movement and event statements respectively (albeit
                based on much smaller sample sizes): movement statements seem to be mostly
                ‘unordered’ (13 out of 24, or 54 percent), while event statements seem mostly ‘flat’
                (22 out of 52, or 42 percent).</p>
            <table-wrap id="mah9dpmvtk3o">
                <label>Table 4.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Frequency distribution of the hierarchical structure present in the
                        location descriptions</title>
                </caption>
                <table id="tbl-bejhalq2i1yw" frame="box" rules="all" cellpadding="5">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>flat</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>strict zoom in</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>partial zoom in</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>partial zoom out</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>strict zoom out</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>unordered</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>total</p></th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>all</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>63</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>42</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>23</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>38</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>81</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>271</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>proper place descriptions</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>29</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>16</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>19</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>30</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>61</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>195</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>movement</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>3</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>13</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>24</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>events</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>22</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>0</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>52</p></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p id="zc5gx7tkmmrh">Finally, <xref ref-type="table" rid="roqvqn4bphr">Table 5</xref>
                shows the frequency distribution of the spatial relationships expressed in the
                analyzed statements. Again, this analysis was only performed for the proper place
                descriptions; it is worth remembering that there might be more than one spatial
                relationship expressed in a single statement. Indeed, 302 spatial relationships are
                observed in the 195 proper place descriptions, a third of which describe a
                topological relationship (e.g., sentence 28: “There was in the forum of the Antiates
                a temple of Castor and Pollux […]”, or sentence 142: “Caieta has always had an
                excellent harbour on its bay […]”). Often, Biondo also localizes entities by
                describing how they relate to other (possibly better known) entities in the
                surroundings. This may lead to rather elaborate descriptions, such as in sentence
                85: “For it was separated from the mainland by swamps, which were cut off by the
                river flowing from the Mons Albinus […]”, or in sentence 107: “Even now part of the
                Pontine Marsh lies next to Terracina, where the swamp is formed by two rivers, the
                larger of which is called Aufens and at Terracina the Via Appia first touches the
                Mare Inferum.”</p>
            <table-wrap id="roqvqn4bphr">
                <label>Table 5.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Frequency distribution of the spatial relationships expressed in the
                        proper place descriptions</title>
                </caption>
                <table id="tbl-ckn4p12l5yb" frame="box" rules="all" cellpadding="5">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Description</p></th>
                            <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Frequency</p></th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="uehi45sr97gt">topology</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p id="abv1dpr4sa8d">102</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>relative orientation</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>86</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>qualitative distance</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>69</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>quantitative distance</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>36</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>correspondence</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>10</p></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-tb9eaglxqi" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>5. Discussion</title>
            <p id="ss2gwo8iyys">As already mentioned in the Methods section, the text’s main aim (at
                least on the surface) seems to be to localize towns and settlements within the
                region of Latium. References to entities on this level of granularity are most
                frequent, with over one third of all references made. Adding to this, those
                references made on the level of geographic feature account for more than half of all
                references made. The latter are relevant here because towns are often localized
                relative to their surroundings, with, for example, towns being located along roads
                (e.g., sentence 144: “And the first city on the road is Fundana […]”), or on a hill
                (e.g., sentence 194: “Five miles from here is the town of Somninum, set on a steep
                hill […]”). Accordingly, there are only very few references to entities on the
                finest levels of granularity, namely furniture and room, since such entities are
                considerably smaller than towns. References on these levels only occur in parts of
                the text where Biondo digresses from a ‘true’ description of the region’s geography,
                or where they otherwise provide some relevant information. For example, sentence 180
                (“Recently, in the town which is corruptly called ‘Civita Indivina’ and is owned by
                cardinal Prospero Columna, a stone inscribed in capital letters was found, which
                shows that that town is Lanuvium”) highlights the discovery of a stone (categorized
                on the furniture level), since that stone provides important evidence for its
                historic name (and Biondo’s justification for using it).</p>
            <p id="tb68csmvg7cn">Looking at hierarchical structures expressed in the descriptions,
                it is notable that in most descriptions no clear structure is apparent. Many are
                either ‘flat’, often because they simply localize towns with respect to each other
                (e.g., sentence 285: “Then there are Cellae, Sculcula and Peretum , from where one
                can descend to Taliacotium”), or they are ‘unordered’, i.e., go back and forth
                between granularity levels – effectively zooming in and out again or vice versa
                (e.g., sentence 320: “On the right bank of the Aniensis – from this Lake Sublacum to
                the Vicus Varronis – one sees an aqueduct cut into the rock of the mountain[…]”).
                The former can be interpreted as another indicator that Biondo’s focus is on the
                towns of the region. The latter seems mostly attributable to his writing style,
                which tends to use a lot of insertions and diversions (e.g., sentence 321: “[…]in
                fact Tibur, in the place where there is the temple of Hercules, has a waterfall,
                which is created by the Anio, as it falls from a very high point into a deep valley
                passing from the woods next to the city itself, where it starts to be navigable”).
                These insertions break up an ordered hierarchical structure, arguably often without
                necessarily supporting a better understanding of the locations described in the
                statement. Indeed, these ‘disruptions’ to an orderly hierarchical structure still
                occurred even after sentences were divided into individual statements (i.e.,
                self-contained descriptions), before the analysis.</p>
            <p id="w73drmjy4k9a">Movement and event statements<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22"
                    >22</xref> seem to fall at either end of this spectrum: more than half of all
                movement statements are unordered, while a good 40 percent of all event statements
                are flat.</p>
            <p id="gbkae4o5vrzs">In terms of spatial relationships (topology, orientation, distance,
                correspondence), results are largely as were to be expected. A third of them are
                topological relations, which might not be surprising given that Biondo’s aim is to
                localize entities, mostly towns, which are <italic>in</italic> a region or
                    <italic>on</italic> a hill. But there are a number of quantitative distance
                relations (about ten percent of all relations), which is interesting to note in what
                is essentially a <italic>qualitative</italic> description such as this text
                provides.</p>
            <p id="w2uyvdo8pcqa">Looking more closely at the chapter, the description of the region
                Latium can be seen as being divided into three parts: the coastline, the inland, and
                the region around Rome. The description of the coastline follows (more or less) a
                linear course from north to south. On the other hand, the inland region is described
                following the course of three main roads – the Via Appia, Via Latina, and Via
                Tibertina (sentence 176: “But we shall adopt another, which will meet our needs
                better and which cannot be applied to other regions of Italy: by proceeding along
                the three roads – Appia, Latina and Tibertina – which by different routes will lead
                to the river Liris and to Sinuessa and Caieta”). Both ways of structuring the
                description of the coast and inland lead to a linear progression. But using main
                roads as a structuring principle may lend itself more naturally to using
                quantitative distances, since along these roads there were/are distance markers
                (milestones). However, looking at the data, no such differences can be found: for
                the coastline 17 out of 80 descriptions (21.25 percent) refer to quantitative
                distances; along the roads there are 19 out of 102 (18.63 percent). In fact, for
                none of the different types of spatial relationships are there any notable
                differences between the different parts of the chapter.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-j5mvudq4cj" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>6. Caveats: Limitations of the Approach</title>
            <p id="xesill9ixav8">The study presented in this chapter has several limitations. Some
                of them are specific to this particular case study, some apply rather to the general
                analytical approach.</p>
            <p id="pqhg3j5yb3r">First, the analysis has been performed on an English translation of
                the Latin original. No attempts have been made to cross-check it with the original
                    text.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref> While this English translation was
                specifically produced with an eye to capturing spatial aspects and geographic
                entities and can thus be taken as true to the original in content and meaning, the
                exact spatial prepositions used and the exact order of spatial references in the
                statements nevertheless matter for the results of the quantitative analysis. Shifts
                in that order, which may be grammatically necessary in the translation (Latin, for
                example, uses a case system rather than prepositions to denote syntactical
                relationships) would lead to different hierarchical structures between the Latin
                original and English translation. It is difficult to judge whether and how often
                this may actually occur between the two texts.</p>
            <p id="ihy5bt0en0zd">Further, the analysis has only been performed by the present author
                of this article. In an analytical approach such as this, however, the annotations
                should be checked by someone other than the author. This is usually done by
                performing an interrater agreement test. Two or three ‘naive raters’ – persons
                unfamiliar with the particular text and research questions – are provided with
                instructions on how to annotate a given corpus (e.g., the Biondo chapter). After
                annotating (a sample of) the corpus, these ‘naive’ annotations are analyzed. The
                extent to which they (dis)agree sheds light on the clarity and usefulness of the
                instructions, helps to identify difficult or ambiguous cases, and serves as a way of
                double-checking how consistently and correctly the annotations were in general – not
                only those of the naive raters, but also those of the ‘experts’ doing the actual
                analysis. Since the main purpose of this chapter is to introduce, motivate, and
                demonstrate this kind of cognitive-structural analysis to an audience probably
                largely unfamiliar with such quantitative approaches in the first place, such an
                interrater agreement analysis was not deemed crucial in this case, but would
                certainly be a topic for future research.</p>
            <p id="m1k9n1ts69wu">As a general limitation, the presented approach separates a text,
                or corpus more generally, into individual statements, which are then analyzed ‘out
                of context’, i.e., each statement is looked at individually without accounting for
                its embedding in the text. This has several consequences. Pronouns that may refer
                back to entities mentioned in a previous statement are ignored, i.e., there is no
                entity resolution, replacing a pronoun with what it refers to. Moreover, such a
                statement-by-statement analysis leads to a very literal reading of the text. As the
                statements are taken out of their local context, their content is taken at surface
                value for what it is; except in obvious cases, no interpretation is attempted of any
                metaphors or figures of speech. This can be seen as a general limitation of this
                kind of analysis. It may be furthermore worth noting that in this specific case, a
                number of cited ancient sources were also disregarded for closer analysis.</p>
            <p id="jwkp0pc1x09">Finally, as it currently stands, the presented approach to analyzing
                location descriptions requires substantial manual processing. This is necessary
                because, despite the decontextualization that ensues through a
                statement-by-statement analysis, there nevertheless remain many decisions that
                depend on the semantics and context within a single statement. Correctly handling
                these poses challenges to machine intelligence as it requires a ‘proper’
                understanding of the text. Having said this, there are parts of the analysis that
                could indeed be better supported by (semi-)automatic processing, for example,
                splitting sentences at punctuation marks (“;”, “:”) and highlighting potential split
                points, i.e., conjunctions (e.g., “and”). Further, pre-annotations could be
                performed by automatically assigning spatial relations (e.g., topology or
                qualitative distance) whenever the relevant prepositions appear (see <xref
                    ref-type="table" rid="ptr5s9qtqt9">Table 2</xref> above). A similar
                pre-annotation could even be performed for the different levels of granularity by
                matching entity names (e.g., names of towns, lakes, or regions) to relevant
                topographic data – so called gazetteers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>
                However, such matching will never be perfect due to ambiguity and other issues.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref> On the one hand, these steps would result in
                a significant part of the annotations being done automatically. On the other hand,
                all the automatic annotations would need to be carefully checked afterwards by the
                researchers to verify consistency and correctness. It remains to be seen which
                workflow is more productive.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="Agnew.1987">
                <label>Agnew 1987</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Agnew</surname>
                            <given-names>John A.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1987</year>
                    <article-title>Place and Politics: The Geographical Mediation of State and
                        Society</article-title><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4324/9781315756585</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Biondo.2005">
                <label>Biondo 2005a</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Biondo</surname>
                            <given-names>Flavio</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Castner</surname>
                            <given-names>Catherine J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Biondo Flavio’s Italia illustrata: Text, Translation, and
                        Commentary</article-title>
                    <volume>1: Northern Italy</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Biondo.2005b">
                <label>Biondo 2005b</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Biondo</surname>
                            <given-names>Flavio</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>White</surname>
                            <given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Italy Illuminated: Books I-IV</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Biondo.2010">
                <label>Biondo 2010</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Biondo</surname>
                            <given-names>Flavio</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Castner</surname>
                            <given-names>Catherine J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <article-title>Biondo Flavio’s Italia illustrata: Text, Translation, and
                        Commentary</article-title>
                    <volume>2: Central and southern Italy</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Biondo.2016">
                <label>Biondo 2016</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Biondo</surname>
                            <given-names>Flavio</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>White</surname>
                            <given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2016</year>
                    <article-title>Italy Illuminated: Books V-VIII</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Derungs.2013">
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <label>Derungs/Purves 2013</label>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Derungs</surname>
                            <given-names>Curdin</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Purves</surname>
                            <given-names>Ross S.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2013</year>
                    <article-title>From Text to Landscape: Locating, Identifying and Mapping the Use
                        of Landscape Features in a Swiss Alpine Corpus</article-title>
                    <source>International Journal of Geographical Information Science</source>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                    <fpage>1272</fpage>
                    <lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13658816.2013.772184</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Goerz.2018">
                <label>Görz et al. 2018</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Görz</surname>
                            <given-names>Günther</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Geus</surname>
                            <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Michalsky</surname>
                            <given-names>Tanja</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2018</year>
                    <article-title>Spatial Cognition in Historical Geographical Texts and Maps:
                        Towards a Cognitive-Semantic Analysis of Flavio Biondo’s Italia
                        Illustrata</article-title>
                    <source>e-Perimetron</source>
                    <volume>13.4</volume>
                    <fpage>182</fpage>
                    <lpage>199</lpage>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="url"
                        xlink:href="http://e-perimetron.org/Vol_13_4/Goerz_et_al.pdf"
                        >Online</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Goerz.2022">
                <label>Görz/Seidl/Thiering 2022</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Görz</surname>
                            <given-names>Guenther</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Seidl</surname>
                            <given-names>Chiara</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>

                    <year>2022</year>
                    <article-title>Linked Biondo: Generating and Processing Research Data Based on
                        Geographical Feature Modeling</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Michalsky</surname>
                            <given-names>Tanja</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Walking through history. An Interdisciplinary Approach to Flavio
                        Biondo’s Spaces in the Italia Illustrata</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48431/hsah.0102</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Grice.1975">
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Grice</surname>
                            <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1975</year>
                    <article-title>Logic and Conversation</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Cole</surname>
                            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Morgan</surname>
                            <given-names>Jerry L.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Speech Acts</source>
                    <fpage>41</fpage>
                    <lpage>58</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Guckelsberger.2022">
                <label>Guckelsberger/Geus 2022</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Guckelsberger</surname>
                            <given-names>Kurt</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Geus</surname>
                            <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2022</year>
                    <article-title>Measurements, Maps, and Other Source Material in Biondo’s Italia
                        Illustrata: The Example of Latium</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Michalsky</surname>
                            <given-names>Tanja</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Walking through history. An Interdisciplinary Approach to Flavio
                        Biondo’s Spaces in the Italia Illustrata</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48431/hsah.0103</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Hirtle.1985">
                <label>Hirtle/Jonides 1985</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Hirtle</surname>
                            <given-names>Stephen C.</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Jonides</surname>
                            <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1985</year>
                    <article-title>Evidence of Hierarchies in Cognitive Maps</article-title>
                    <source>Memory &amp; Cognition</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>208</fpage>
                    <lpage>217</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Plumert.2001">
                <label>Plumert/Spalding/Nichols-Whitehead 2001</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Plumert</surname>
                            <given-names>Jodie M.</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Spalding</surname>
                            <given-names>Thomas L.</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Nichols-Whitehead</surname>
                            <given-names>Penney</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Preferences for Ascending and Descending Hierarchical
                        Organization in Spatial Communication</article-title>
                    <source>Memory &amp; Cognition</source>
                    <volume>2</volume>
                    <issue>29</issue>
                    <fpage>274</fpage>
                    <lpage>284</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Richter.2013c">
                <label>Richter D./Winter et al. 2013</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Richter</surname>
                            <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Winter</surname>
                            <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Richter</surname>
                            <given-names>Kai-Florian</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Stirling</surname>
                            <given-names>Lesley</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2013</year>
                    <article-title>Granularity of Locations Referred to by Place
                        Descriptions</article-title>
                    <source>Computers, Environment and Urban Systems</source>
                    <volume>41</volume>
                    <fpage>88</fpage>
                    <lpage>99</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2013.03.005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Richter.2013b">
                <label>Richter D./Vasardani et al. 2013</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Richter</surname>
                            <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Vasardani</surname>
                            <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Stirlng</surname>
                            <given-names>Lesley</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Richter</surname>
                            <given-names>Kai-Florian</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Winter</surname>
                            <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2013</year>
                    <article-title>Zooming In – Zooming Out: Hierarchies in Place
                        Descriptions</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Krisp</surname>
                            <given-names>Jukka M.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Progress in Location-Based Services</source>
                    <fpage>339</fpage>
                    <lpage>355</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-34203-5_19</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Shanon.1979">
                <label>Shanon 1979</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Shanon</surname>
                            <given-names>Benny</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1979</year>
                    <article-title>Where Questions</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Sondheimer</surname>
                            <given-names>Norman</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Proceedings of the 17th Annual Meeting of the Association of
                        Computational Linguistics</source>
                    <fpage>73</fpage>
                    <lpage>75</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3115/982163.982183</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Svorou.1994">
                <label>Svorou 1994</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Svorou</surname>
                            <given-names>Soteria</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>The Grammar of Space</article-title>
                    <volume>25</volume>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1075/tsl.25</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>


            <ref id="Talmy.1983">
                <label>Talmy 1983</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Talmy</surname>
                            <given-names>Leonard</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1983</year>
                    <article-title>How Language Structures Space</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Pick Jr</surname>
                            <given-names>Herbert L.</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Acredolo</surname>
                            <given-names>Linda P.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Spatial Orientation: Theory, Research and Application</source>
                    <fpage>225</fpage>
                    <lpage>282</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4615-9325-6_11</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Thiering.2015">
                <label>Thiering 2015</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2015</year>
                    <article-title>Spatial Semiotics and Spatial Mental Models: Figure-Ground
                        Asymmetries in Language</article-title>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/9783110356878</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Thiering.2022">
                <label>Thiering/Berthele 2022</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Berthele</surname>
                            <given-names>Raphael</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2022</year>
                    <article-title>Some Thoughts on a Spatial Language Analysis of Flavio Biondo’s
                        Illustrated Italy</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Michalsky</surname>
                            <given-names>Tanja</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Walking through history. An Interdisciplinary Approach to Flavio
                        Biondo’s Spaces in the Italia Illustrata</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48431/hsah.0107</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Vasardani.2013c">
                <label>Vasardani/Winter/Richter K.F. 2013</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Vasardani</surname>
                            <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Winter</surname>
                            <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Richter</surname>
                            <given-names>Kai-Florian</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2013</year>
                    <article-title>Locating Place Names from Place Descriptions</article-title>
                    <source>International Journal of Geographical Information Science</source>
                    <volume>12</volume>
                    <fpage>2509</fpage>
                    <lpage>2532</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13658816.2013.785550</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Winter.2011">
                <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Winter</surname>
                            <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Richter</surname>
                            <given-names>Kai-Florian</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Baldwin</surname>
                            <given-names>Tim</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Cavedon</surname>
                            <given-names>Lawrence</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Stirling</surname>
                            <given-names>Lesley</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Duckham</surname>
                            <given-names>Matt</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Kealy</surname>
                            <given-names>Allison</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Rajabifard</surname>
                            <given-names>Abbas</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <article-title>Location-Based Mobile Games for Spatial Knowledge
                        Acquisition</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Janowicz</surname>
                            <given-names>Krzystof</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Krüger</surname>
                            <given-names>Antonio</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Raubal</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Keßler</surname>
                            <given-names>Carsten</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Proceedings of the Workshop on Cognitive Engineering for Mobile
                        GIS</source><uri xlink:href="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-780/paper1.pdf">http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-780/paper1.pdf</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <fn-group content-type="footnotes">
            <title>Footnotes</title>
            <fn id="fn1">
                <label>1</label>
                <p>Place is a somewhat elusive concept that does not just capture ‘objective’
                    geographic reality, for example, topography. It is often defined as encompassing
                    three aspects, respectively termed locale (its shaping through human activity),
                    sense of place (its character, its meaning to people), and location (where it is
                    on the earth’s surface); see, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr"
                        rid="Agnew.1987">(Agnew 1987)</xref>. In the present chapter, however, the
                    focus is on the location aspect of place. Accordingly, we will mainly use
                    location as a term in the remainder of this text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
                <label>2</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013c">(Richter D./Winter et al.
                    2013)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
                <label>3</label>
                <p>In other contexts, also sometimes called “degree of specificity”; Cf. <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Svorou.1994">(Svorou 1994)</xref>; <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Thiering.2015">(Thiering 2015)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
                <label>4</label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Shanon.1979">(Shanon 1979)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
                <label>5</label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Plumert.2001">(Plumert/Spalding/Nichols-Whitehead
                        2001)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kfux9aw9vxmg">
                <label>6</label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Hirtle.1985">(Hirtle/Jonides 1985)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
                <label>7</label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Talmy.1983">(Talmy 1983)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="svmht4we0wzt">
                <label>8</label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Grice.1975">(Grice 1975)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="czm2px93xu9p">
                <label>9</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2005b">(Biondo 2005b)</xref>; <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2016">(Biondo 2016)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
                <label>10</label>
                <p>In fact, the approach seems to be applicable to both synchronic and diachronic
                    data.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
                <label>11</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Winter.2011">(Winter et al.
                        2011)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013c">(Richter D./Winter
                        et al. 2013)</xref>; and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013b">(Richter
                        D./Vasardani et al. 2013)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
                <label>12</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2005b">(Biondo 2005b, 118–202)</xref>, see also <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2005">(Biondo 2005a)</xref> and <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2010">(Biondo 2010)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
                <label>13</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Goerz.2018">(Görz et al. 2018)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
                <label>14</label>
                <p>Note that not every appearance of a conjunctive term or punctuation mark requires
                    splitting a sentence. Often “and” is used as part of an enumeration, for
                    example. Therefore, a naive automatic splitting using these terms and marks
                    would not guarantee results in a meaningful set of statements.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="qy7p91jfxjyl">
                <label>15</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013c">(Richter D./Winter et al. 2013)</xref>;
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013b">(Richter D./Vasardani et al.
                        2013)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
                <label>16</label>
                <p>The descriptions were specifically collected for the purpose of that analysis;
                    thus, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013c">(Richter D./Winter et al.
                        2013)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013b">(Richter D./Vasardani
                        et al. 2013)</xref>, took a synchronic point of view.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="zx35zsz0d8bh">
                <label>17</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013b">(Richter D./Vasardani et al. 2013,
                        343–44)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="sc1h6ueh55xl">
                <label>18</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Richter.2013c">(Richter D./Winter et al.
                    2013)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
                <label>19</label>
                <p>The Latin text would use the locative, ablative, and allative case to encode
                    spatial relations.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
                <label>20</label>
                <p>For more, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Thiering.2022">(Thiering/Berthele
                        2022)</xref> in this volume.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
                <label>21</label>
                <p>The uniqueness of entities, or their frequency of being mentioned, has not been
                    further analyzed, but may provide a further interesting aspect to look at in the
                    future.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
                <label>22</label>
                <p>See the discussion of trajectories above.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
                <label>23</label>
                <p>See however, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Goerz.2022">(Görz/Seidl/Thiering
                        2022)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Guckelsberger.2022"
                        >(Guckelsberger/Geus 2022)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr"
                        rid="Thiering.2022">(Thiering/Berthele 2022)</xref> in this volume.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
                <label>24</label>
                <p>There are tools and frameworks available that may allow for some of these steps
                    to be done as outlined here, for example, Recogito (URL: <ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://recogito.pelagios.org"
                        >https://recogito.pelagios.org</ext-link>). See, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Goerz.2022">(Görz/Seidl/Thiering
                        2022)</xref> in this volume, who use the BRAT
                    semi-automated annotation tool.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
                <label>25</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Derungs.2013"> (Derungs/Purves 2013)</xref>; <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Vasardani.2013c">(Vasardani/Winter/Richter K.F.
                        2013)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
        </fn-group>
    </back>
</article>
