<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.3 20210610//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.3/JATS-journalpublishing1-3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en-US" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="original-article" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HSAH</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Hertziana Studies in Art History</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title>HSAH</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn/>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Bibliotheca Hertziana - Max Planck Institute for Art
                    History</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.48431/hsah.0104</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel">
                    <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Two Great Maps of Italy – A Comparison</article-title>
                <alt-title>Two Great Maps of Italy</alt-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"  deceased="no"
                    id="jfgbhjbdaj">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Guckelsberger</surname>
                        <given-names>Kurt</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <email>kurt.guckelsberger@gmx.de</email>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="affjbacjgecgig"/>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr-jfgbhjbdaj">‐</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="affjbacjgecgig"><institution content-type="orgname">Freie
                        Universität</institution><institution content-type="orgdiv1"
                        >Friedrich-Meinecke-Institut</institution><addr-line/><city>Berlin</city><country>Germany</country></aff>
            </contrib-group>
            <author-notes>
                <corresp id="corr-jfgbhjbdaj">Corresponding author:
                        <email>kurt.guckelsberger@gmx.de</email></corresp>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>31</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2022</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <elocation-id>4</elocation-id>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>28</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>28</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2020</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>This material is distributed under the terms of the Creative
                    Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
                    reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
                    cited.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Bibliotheca Hertziana - Max Planck Institute for Art
                    History</copyright-holder>
                <license license-type="open-access"
                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                    <license-p>This work is licensed under Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                        International (CC BY 4.0).</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <p id="nd5uycwbx7hp">Two large maps, contemporary with Flavio Biondo's
                        <italic>Italia Illustrata</italic>, create a rather comprehensive image of
                    Italy. In this paper, I show that the Cotton Roll XIII.44 of the British Library
                    is put together from two maps of different scale: one for Italy north of Rome
                    and a smaller scale for southern Italy. It displays more than 1200 toponyms and
                    six-thousand kilometres of rivers. The second map, Ms.1816 of the University of
                    Strasbourg, is almost identical to the northern part in content. Devoid of
                    political boundaries, there is no orography and an unusual flat hierarchy of
                    icons. Despite large differences in appearance, they share a common data base.
                    Both derive probably from a lost master chart. Despite necessary overlap,
                    Biondo's regional inventories differ substantially. He may have seen these maps
                    but he did not rely on them.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
                <kwd>Common sense geography</kwd>
                <kwd>maps</kwd>
                <kwd>measurements</kwd>
                <kwd>Biondo</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="import-t4bd2ez6ei" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>1. Introduction</title>
            <p id="znwd9fjvj3s">This article makes the case that two of the seven “grandi carte
                d’Italia” of the early fifteenth century, proposed as a subgenre of historical maps
                by Marica Milanesi in her talk in 2006,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="omc47vnulsv"
                    >1</xref> evolved from a common but yet unknown source document or ‘ancestor’.
                Indeed, the map known by its shelf mark as Cotton Roll XIII.44 now in the British
                Library (henceforth “the Cotton”) and manuscript Ms.1.816 at the Bibliothèque
                nationale et universitaire (henceforth “the Strasbourg”) share a large part of their
                toponyms, rivers, size, and general layout characteristics. Both appear as a visual
                complement to the textual vision of Flavio Biondo’s <italic>Italia
                    Illustrata</italic>, namely a complete survey of mainland Italy from the Alpine
                arc to the Ionian Sea, albeit with different coverage areas. The present study is
                part of the quest for the maps Biondo used as sources for his seminal work
                    <italic>Italia Illustrata</italic>. As shown in a companion paper (Guckelsberger
                and Geus),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="zau1nngk39qa">2</xref> Biondo reports more than
                2000 toponyms, far outnumbering the labeling on any map of the fifteenth century
                hitherto known and discussed – except one: the Cotton, with its 1220 vignettes
                denoting settlements, from single buildings to large cities. In addition, an
                extended river system provides hundreds of landmarks for orientation and
                localization, such as springs and sources, confluences and estuaries. Strangely
                enough, this early masterpiece of Venetian terrestrial mapmaking, has somehow
                largely escaped historical attention, with very few scholars making any reference to
                it over the centuries. Perhaps to Italian scholars it was not easily accessible due
                to its location in the British Library, where, although carefully preserved, it was
                presumably perceived as ‘just another’ (albeit interesting) map of Italy, one among
                    thousands.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref> Even scarcer are studies of the
                Strasbourg map, which also escaped historical attention, perhaps arguably due to its
                poor preservation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref> Hence it was a surprise
                that both maps – or rather what has survived of them – share almost identical
                content, shape, and size, albeit presented in radically different styles. This
                discovery opens a new window on early European mapmaking and ‘database studies’.
                Early on in this study, it became clear that, despite the richness of content and
                obvious overlap, Biondo certainly did not use either of these two particular maps,
                as in many areas the structure and content are widely different in both Biondo’s
                text and the maps. However, Milanesi recently showed that Biondo must have used or
                consulted the Cotton – or a very similar map – in one particular region at least,
                namely in the Rhaetian Alps.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref> Biondo’s accounts
                of three rivers – the Adda, Oglio, and the River Non (a tributary of the Adige) –
                share a common error with the Cotton: the rivers appear to rise from a single
                source, which is not possible because they are separated by passes. This error is
                unique to the Cotton because the mutilated Strasbourg shows only the passage of the
                Oglio across the Passo Tonale to the Noce river, and on other surviving maps (and in
                chorographical texts), the connection of the Oglio and the Adda across the Passo
                Gavia persisted into the sixteenth century. The discovery that Biondo must have
                studied a Cotton-like map (if not the Cotton itself) and the fact that we have two
                surviving artifacts displaying quite different versions hints at other maps of
                similarly grand design that have, however, since perished. This all suggests that in
                both the Cotton and Strasbourg, a big effort was made to map the whole Italian
                peninsula in detail, on a scale greater than the known regional maps. It surely was
                an expensive enterprise to collect quite precise information on distance and
                direction for more than 6000 kilometers of nearly every river of Italy – including
                all tributaries – and collate and design a consistent image without the required
                cartographic and surveying tools of the coming centuries.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn6">6</xref> The scope, reach, and erudition of the two maps equal or
                better complement the ambition and mental image of a unified Italy as embodied in
                Biondo’s <italic>Italia Illustrata</italic>.</p>
            <p id="y4ssrh8phcee">In the following, I will give a very brief overview of the main
                characteristics of the Cotton on a somewhat numerical basis to establish its
                outstanding properties before exploring the familial relationship between the two
                uneven ‘sisters’. Although the Strasbourg covers the peninsula only down to Rome,
                both objects share an outline of Italy clearly derived from portolan charts with a
                rich and (relatively) precise mapping of settlements, rivers, and lakes in the
                interior. Thus, they uniquely combine the outlines of a maritime chart with the
                content of a truly land-based map. This clearly distinguishes them from the numerous
                maps created in the second half of the fifteenth century which use the
                (geographically inaccurate) outlines of Italy as described by Ptolemy in the third
                book of his <italic>Geography.</italic> This fundamental change in fifteenth century
                cartography is deeply rooted in the work of Donnus Nicolaus Germanus, a German monk
                who arrived in Florence around 1460.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref> In his
                (and others’) <italic>tabulae novae</italic> (or <italic>tabulae modernae</italic>),
                he interpolated between known ancient sites many new towns unknown in Antiquity.
                Prior to this shift, early humanists apparently completely ignored the first book,
                in which Ptolemy explains the mathematics required to properly project the spherical
                coordinates of a spherical Earth onto a flat surface with minimal distortions.</p>
            <p id="okonbp8azp2">Early fifteenth-century cartography is generally associated with
                Venetian craftsmanship in providing increasingly reliable maps for religious,
                economic, and military enterprises (Crusades and long-distance trade). They were
                soon augmented by the works of mapmakers based in Genoa, Mallorca, and other
                predominantly maritime communities. Known as portolan charts, this genre of nautical
                map survived for roughly the next 400 years. Relying predominantly on landmarks on
                shorelines and associated settlements and river mouths, they rarely showed
                settlements of the interior. As a result, maps of whole countries were generally
                less known. In chapter 20 of the extremely influential <italic>History of
                    Cartography</italic>, published in 1987, P.A.D. Harvey writes:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="owyj4kvf6wn">A very few are maps of entire countries: the maps of Palestine,
                    the Matthew Paris and Gough maps of Britain, the maps of Germany and central
                    Europe by Nicolas of Cusa and Erhard Etzlaub. But most are maps of small
                        areas.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref></p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="ipzg6z5u1wt">Harvey goes on to list in appendix 20.1 only eight regional maps of
                Italy, without mentioning either of our maps.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="rflxrxtcellu"
                    >9</xref> After discussing Paolino Veneto’s map of Italy of circa 1340,
                containing few toponyms, he continues:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="e7yeaz01xraf">[I]t is not until the fifteenth century that we find further
                    detailed maps of the whole of Italy. Two seem to be unique productions, but five
                    others form a single series of closely related maps from which further maps were
                    indeed derived in the early sixteenth century. Three of the five occur in copies
                    of Ptolemy’s <italic>Geography</italic> [...]<xref ref-type="fn"
                        rid="a6jhs3mdko4h">10</xref></p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="i09upoqsbkyhg">By leaving out all details, it might be that these ‘obscure’
                specimens indeed refer to our maps. Later, in 2006, Milanesi suggested a generic
                name, the “grandi carte d’Italia”, mostly due to their common large size.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="zdm1u14t6vci">11</xref> They usually measure at least 110
                centimeters in height and are designed to a scale of around 1:1.8–1:2 for the size
                of the peninsula, measured horizontally between Nice and Pola and the Simplon Pass
                to Cape Leuca at the southern end. This is comparable to the map scale of 1:1.9 of a
                modern-day sheet map. Taking into account the actual size of Italy, this gives us an
                average scale of approximately 1:600,000 or 6 kilometers/centimeter. According to
                Milanesi, several of these seven maps had a distinct purpose: displayed in
                antechambers of princely palaces they had to demonstrate the mastery of territory
                and superior knowledge of the prince, or, in the case of Venice, the magistrate.
                Only these seven specimens have survived. Considering the ‘natural habitat’ of such
                maps, princely <italic>palazzi</italic>, the two maps presented here form an
                unlikely couple. The Cotton is a spectacular display-piece, which Peter Barber,
                recently retired Head of Map Collections at the British Library, believes was
                probably presented as a gift to the English king sometime in the fifteenth century
                (personal communication, February 6, 2018). More than 1200 toponyms, 64 river
                systems, and carefully crafted miniature vignettes characterize this outstanding
                testament to terrestrial cartography. By displaying subtle designations of rank
                instead of crude (even brutal) representations of the size of the powers that be,
                and by ignoring political boundaries and adopting a remarkably precise scale (albeit
                of a shifting magnitude), it is a unique early ‘topographic’ enterprise. It shares
                the same vision of a united Italy from the Alpine watershed to the Ionian Sea
                (subsequently only realized in 1919 with the annexation of Trentino-Alto Adige but
                already described by Ptolemy), as cited both by the author of the Cotton in the
                first sentence of the text accompanying the map and by Biondo in <italic>Italia
                    Illustrata</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="vl8u5xiba41">12</xref></p>
            <p id="j2uytz0mvn98">In the following, I focus on the geographical ‘ground truth’ by
                first presenting the Cotton’s main features – the coastline, the settlements, and
                the river system – followed by a description of the Strasbourg map with its unique
                grid system and a discussion of its southern end. Following this I explore the
                similarities between the two maps by first looking at the coastlines and then at
                possible distortions in the parchment and cotton support which may have altered the
                images, quite independent of the mapmaker’s original intentions. The probability of
                a common source is discussed and, lastly, some of the remaining differences are
                highlighted, such as the drawing of the rivers, the rendering of extended objects,
                including a strange ‘mutilation’ of the Strasbourg.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-k6yufx7niy" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>2. The Description of Italy by the Cotton</title>
            <p id="fi12xemarq7o">From a geographical, cartographical, and historical point of view,
                the Cotton map is of the highest interest and helps in understanding contemporary
                attitudes toward all three fields of learning. In this paper, the emphasis is on the
                historical perspective in relation to Biondo’s project of <italic>Italia
                    Illustrata</italic>. However, it adds to our understanding if one also considers
                the two other facets – the geographical and cartographical – in gaining further
                insight into the problems Biondo probably faced when setting out on his agenda. In
                that respect, for a terrestrial map of the early fifteenth century, the Cotton’s
                ‘vital statistics’ are nothing less than impressive when one considers all three
                points of view. The two diagrams combined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="l8srh33gvqx4"
                    >fig. 1</xref> best summarize the extraordinary craftsmanship involved.</p>
            <fig id="l8srh33gvqx4" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>The Cotton in outline. </title>
                    <p>The left diagram shows the locations of all 1220 vignettes. The 100 cities
                        highlighted with two or more doors are shown with circles of ca 30km radius.
                        The right diagram traces part of the extensive river system of more than
                        8000 km.</p>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_01.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_01.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="yb2erxc0v145">Three main elements come together:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                    <p id="t7srukggwp6i">The outline is apparently derived from portolan charts. It
                        features 245 littoral points: 191 harbors – coastal towns (some of them in
                        the interior, as represented on all maritime charts of the time) – and 54
                        estuaries, good for shelter or up-river travel. Distributed over about 3450
                        kilometers from the mouth of the Isonzo to mouth of the Var in what is now
                        France, it covers every 14 kilometers of the ‘lay of the land’, or more
                        precisely, the coast. It is richer in detail than contemporary maritime
                        charts: Among these, only 128 (52 percent) are found in Tony Campbell’s
                        ‘magisterial’ list of 2015, which in turn contains 400-plus entries from all
                        portolan charts between Var and Isonzo.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13"
                            >13</xref> From this we can extrapolate that the compilers of the Cotton
                        did not simply copy existing portolan charts but provided more points than
                        the sailors deemed worthy of note. The coastline provides the frame for the
                        other two data compilations, namely the inland settlements and rivers.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p id="bdi30lem1duk">The total number of settlements amounts to 1220. As far as
                        I know, no other fifteenth century map that has come down to us boasts a
                        similar number. Erhard Etzlaub’s <italic>Romweg</italic> map of 1496 of
                        Central Europe to Rome only has 515 marked settlements. The extremely
                        well-studied and publicized Gough Map of Britain displays 600-plus place
                        names, with the exact number no longer determinable as some have faded over
                        the centuries.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref> None of the German
                        fifteenth century maps approaches the 1220 named settlements in the
                            Cotton.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref> Settlement and city rank
                        is expressed through subtle indications in the miniature vignettes. In 288
                        vignettes, roofs are emphasized by a blot of lapis lazuli, the most precious
                        of pigments. However, this color distinction seems not to convey rank,
                        because even some tiny hamlets are so adorned and I could find no
                        correlation between these points with places of power, political or
                        ecclesiastical, in times predating or concurrent to the map. In contrast,
                        for six vignettes, the rendering of three portcullises in the city wall does
                        indeed serve to emphasize the city’s importance. These cities are Rome,
                        Narnia (Narni), Florence, Venice, Verona, and Alessandria.<xref
                            ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref> Another 93 vignettes show two
                        portcullises and all 100 two- or three-portcullis entries represent
                        important cities, from Rome to Urbino or Milan, or similar regional
                        ‘heavyweights’. The remaining vignettes have only one portcullis and pertain
                        to all manner of settlements: important sites ranging from single
                        fortresses, such as the Castello di Canossa, to isolated monasteries,
                        hamlets, and villages, to small towns which have sometimes since dwindled,
                        now with only two or three buildings remaining. In <xref ref-type="fig"
                            rid="l8srh33gvqx4">fig. 1</xref> the 100 important cities are emphasized
                        by a circle representing ‘a day’s ride’ radius of roughly 30 to 40
                        kilometers depending on local scale, to underline the sophistication of the
                        vignette choice. The pattern is still dominated by a large number of port
                        towns and a cluster in the region around Naples.<xref ref-type="fn"
                            rid="fn17">17</xref> In the Papal States, the Tiber river basin does not
                        dominate, but Latium and the Umbrian and Ancona territories stand out,
                        contrasting with a relative paucity in the Po Basin. In the left diagram of
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="l8srh33gvqx4">fig. 1</xref>, one first sees
                        the spine of the Apennine Mountains – especially in the south – separating
                        the central valleys from the coastal plains. Interestingly, an unbroken
                        chain of wealthy towns can be observed, stretching over more than 400
                        kilometers from Sulmona in Abruzzo to Modena and following the ancient Roman
                        roads of the Via Salaria, Via Flaminia, and finally Via Aemilia. Mountainous
                        regions stand out, especially in the foothills of the Alps. The map includes
                        outlines of the Po, Arno, and Tiber rivers and faithfully traces their bends
                        and turns as a further sign of well-researched and detailed features.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                    <p id="kyg2z22j5o4">A network of 6324 kilometers of rivers<xref ref-type="fn"
                            rid="fn18">18</xref> structures the interior into interconnected smaller
                        domains, allowing the mapmaker to plot the settlements’ relative position
                        from each other, using fluctuating local scales in the absence of a uniform
                        scale for the entire area coverage.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>
                        This fluvial scaffold covers 59 rivers emptying into the sea and 67
                        tributaries, with 693 settlements documented on their banks and 139
                        settlements at their mouths.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref> In a
                        sense, this intricate lattice can and probably did stand in for the
                        thoroughly abstract mathematical grid of astronomically determined parallels
                        and meridians proposed some 1200 years earlier by Ptolemy. It was a much
                        simpler mapmaking technique than using a laboriously determined solar
                        altitude (with its considerable scope for error) and a longitude based on
                        pure guesswork.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref> Indeed, Ptolemy’s
                        work was not fully understood or even accepted after its rediscovery in the
                        thirteenth century and would arguably only be so later in the fifteenth
                        century, after the Cotton had been made.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22"
                            >22</xref> After all, in real terms, the adjacent headwaters of the Arno
                        and Tiber provide a satisfactory topographical point of reference, being
                        somewhere halfway between Rimini and Montevarchi.<xref ref-type="fn"
                            rid="fn23">23</xref> However, we also see that the second most important
                        river in Tuscany after the Arno – the Ombrone – has been forgotten
                            entirely.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref> Together with a
                        scarcity of major settlements in the lowlands, one reason for such an
                        omission may well be that the area was of little interest for military and
                        economical enterprises at the time due to the swampy conditions of the
                        terrain and the threat of malaria. As already pointed out by Milanesi, the
                        Cotton’s representation of the coastal plain of Tuscany is much too narrow,
                        implying a rapid scale-change over the last few centimeters before the
                        coast. Another reason for the missing river and spatial inconsistencies may
                        be that the chart was ‘filled in’ from left to right, from the Adriatic
                        toward the Tyrrhenian coast. If the general outline was fixed first, then
                        the impressive crowding of vignettes and their names in the Adriatic half
                        may have crowded out the last entries before the western coast was reached.
                        Against the background of careful execution in the Po Basin, these omissions
                        appear as ad-hoc decisions during the drawing-in phase, not a deliberate
                        truncation for other reasons. Together with flexible scales along the
                        rivers, both features appear as a natural consequence of non-geodesic
                        mapmaking.</p>
                </list-item>
            </list>
            <p id="yb3iruwar06">Such complete coverage as a general map of the peninsula (ignoring
                for the moment some deficiencies and lacunae in the Kingdom of Naples in the south)
                goes far beyond military or economic surveying purposes, during a time characterized
                by a constant struggle for supremacy among rival principalities and states.
                Extensive portolan charts were also expensive but had a completely different
                (linear) background in commerce and warfare, piracy and domination.</p>
            <p id="dg15jnyhjg5h">This leads to the following question: what were the underlying
                intellectual or political ambitions that warranted the financing and commissioning
                of the traveling surveyors, mapmakers, artists, and executioners for such a project
                in early fifteenth-century Venice? (By comparison, it is perhaps worth noting that
                Biondo probably had a variety of helpful assistants but essentially worked
                alone.)</p>
            <p id="lrcx0fiuc1m">The next subsection presents the fascinating subject of how near or
                far the two maps with their almost identical chorographic content resemble each
                other, given their dramatically different appearance. Before doing so, it is first
                necessary to provide a brief description of the Strasbourg map, before embarking on
                a more detailed comparison.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-agmovzhwqw" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>3. A Brief Description of the Strasbourg Map</title>
            <p id="e26zo8l3tvra">Every image, painting, or map, ‘speaks a language’ to communicate
                with its readers or audience. The Cotton (140 x 66 centimeters), for example,
                consists of an elaborate headline “Italie provincie modernus situs”, a laudatory
                text describing the historic excellence of the land – and the map. The image of the
                peninsula is surrounded by beautifully executed sea creatures and a variety of
                maritime scenes. The islands and adjacent countries are indicated by twelve round
                medallions that merely allude to their existence. With gold lettering on lapis
                lazuli for the title, clear calligraphic script, and a precise execution of the
                illustrations, the Cotton conveys a sense of power, confidence, and aesthetic
                ambition.</p>
            <fig id="zhpwdbqqwwc" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>The two images representing Rome in the two maps juxtapose the aesthetic
                        and factual differences between them. The name Roma on the Cotton is nearly
                        obliterated by frequently pointing at it.</title>
                    <p>left Coll. et photogr. BNU de Strasbourg, right (c) British Library</p>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_02.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_02.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="ob0c6nykfvqa">In contrast, the Strasbourg (65 x 95 centimeters) presents a rather
                austere image which is best illustrated with the two vignettes for Rome, both
                fitting into a 3 x 3 centimeter frame. The Cotton has finely crenellated city walls
                and towers (one even flying a flag), a cupola (perhaps the Pantheon?), and steeples.
                The Tiber enters at the front and flows out the other side, thereby creating a more
                natural image of a real city. The Strasbourg map, by contrast, only shows a clumsily
                drawn front of a strange building with the outline of a church with three spires and
                some military apparatus, with the river simply stopping at the left edge of the
                building.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref></p>
            <fig id="mzhilrk15lid" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>The image of the vicinity of Arezzo displays the typical graphical
                        features of the Strasbourg map: The alternately coloured grid-lines, the
                        large vignette and red lettering of important towns (Arezzo), the tiny other
                        vignettes like ulmo below Arezzo and the thin, discontinuous black
                        sketch-line for the rivers with its bluegreen thick enhancement.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_03.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_03.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="wvb9d51xnfk">Also, whereas the Cotton has a finely drawn red frame around the
                cartographic image and is bordered by a carefully drawn, nearly straight initial
                border (see below), the raw outlines of the animal hide, including the neck, are
                good enough for the Strasbourg, and indeed most portolan charts of the time look the
                same. A faded dark-green, rather sloppily applied wash represents the Adriatic and
                Tyrrhenian Sea without any embellishments, whereas the Cotton displays decoratively
                rippling waves and joyful images of dolphins and miniature scenes of busy maritime
                life. In short, the Strasbourg is indeed a poor relative, as Milanesi states.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref></p>
            <p id="sd0c2tm6yf3g">To us today, the Strasbourg looks much like a technical sketch
                rather than a (princely) map. Modern geographers would call it a brouillon (rough
                sketch) that nevertheless contains important data for distance and direction,
                brought back from fieldwork to be turned into a polished draft in the office.</p>
            <p id="wonk2sulexaj">Tiny crenellated vignettes, 3 x 3 millimeters wide, indicate
                settlements and towns. A few important ones are marked in red, with Rome naturally
                the largest. Thin black lines, retraced by a slightly broader green line represent
                rivers and lake outlines; lake surfaces are washed in light grey-green. The sharp
                thin lines, visibly preceding the overlay of color and broader lines for rivers and
                coasts, indicate a preliminary sketch. In many passages, this likely ‘first attempt’
                was not subsequently laid in with the bolder lines of the more visible final image.
                All these features are visible, for example, in the detail around Arezzo in <xref
                    ref-type="fig" rid="mzhilrk15lid">fig. 3</xref>. Here we see the thin sharp
                lines sketched in black along part of the Arno river to the left, emphasized later
                in greenish-grey ink, the tiny crenellated town-vignettes below, the clumsy attempt
                at a vignette in perspective reserved for important towns, including red lettering,
                and finally the alternate coloring of the rhumb lines.</p>
            <fig id="bl8akf0wn9j" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 4.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>This redrawing of the system of terrestrial wind-rose lines visible in MS
                        1.816 shows that the mapmaker developed the classical system of 16-fold
                        symmetry only up to eight nodes plus a central node and using it only in
                        certain places.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_04.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_04.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="r8tf2u9y2uzc">From a modern perspective, the Strasbourg gives the impression of a
                ‘work in progress’. This impression is reinforced by a unique feature for land maps:
                superimposed on the map are three primary, equally spaced land-based sixteen-point
                ‘stars’, placed near Arezzo, Roteglia (near Modena), and Lecco, with additional
                stars placed off-shore from Venice and Genoa, and yet others (albeit incomplete)
                ten-point secondary stars located at the four 45-degree angles from the central star
                near Arezzo.</p>
            <p id="tga0v4bmg6l">They form a set of rectangular cells approximately 24 x 24
                centimeters wide. Where the lines do not help (outside terra firma and beyond
                Fermo), they appear incomplete and peter out, thus suggesting a half-hearted attempt
                to imitate the manner of the portolan charts of the day. Nearly all these maps are
                first sectioned by a central horizontal line extending from the neck to the tail
                forming the west–east axis and a vertical, central line forming the north–south
                    axis.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref> Additional rhumb lines complete
                the wind roses, mostly with a sixteen or thirty-two-fold symmetry. In the
                Strasbourg, there is no relation to geographical north nor to the size of the animal
                skin. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="bl8akf0wn9j">fig. 4</xref> one sees that the
                center line does not form the bisecting axis and the horizontal subdivision does not
                lie halfway down from any discernible future format the mapmaker may have originally
                had in mind. The 45-degree system is marked by a short dotted (. . .) line and the
                bisecting red lines in the original are denoted by dashed lines (- - - ). One has
                the impression that the two vertical markers in the Adriatic and Tyrrhenian Sea are
                merely there to help place the coastal towns and the center line through
                “arezo”/Arezzo and the inland sites. The additional tighter grid at 22.5 degrees
                (with a 9.3 x 9.3 centimeter grid width, roughly equating to 50 x 50 kilometers)
                just happens to somehow organize the landmass into more manageable sections. The
                grid is irregular and appears haphazard and perhaps not well thought out. In short,
                it structures map-space, not the geographical relation of the peninsula with its
                surroundings. Questions as to why, when, and how these markings were made require
                complex historical cartographic study and are therefore excluded from the present
                article. Suffice it to say that this unique map merits further study and opens a
                rare window onto early European mapmaking.</p>
            <p id="wcrmsuiz0gk">Another feature which the Strasbourg shares with portolan charts but
                not with the Cotton is the use of red lettering in the labeling of some cities. On
                his website on the history of cartography, Tony Campbell found that 630 of the grand
                total of 2750 (or 23 percent) of the names collected from portolan charts are
                written in red. He adds:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="ik38dh3s1pxi">As an indicator of responsiveness to political and commercial
                    developments, the red names are a disappointing witness [and] there was little
                    relation between the historical record and the introduction or abandonment of
                    red names.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref></p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="jpdvawjsbfp">On the Strasbourg map, this ratio is 95 out of a total of 649
                vignettes (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="i1q5qy5j4iac">Table. 1</xref>) or only
                14.6 percent (roughly one in seven) and the more sparingly used distinctions
                generally relate to important cities. Such differences suggest that the mapmaker
                liked the lettering in red (probably) seen on portolan charts, but modified the
                criteria for its application on his own map.</p>
            <p id="fhau9m67sajw">Very little is known about the origin of the Strasbourg. It was
                first presented to the public in 1933.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="irrryp9si628"
                    >29</xref> According to records, it was acquired (after 1883) from the estate of
                Karl Witte (Halle), renowned translator and founder of the German Dante Society who
                spent many years in Italy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref> It is possible
                that while in Italy he searched of Biondo’s or Petrarch’s/Dante’s map.
                Characteristics of script and toponyms date the Strasbourg to the Italy of the early
                1400s. Not much else is known and precious little literature has been published on
                the subject.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref></p>
            <p id="onn4fynnbpm">Paraphrasing an earlier study of the northeastern part of the
                country by Franz Grenacher,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="j51g24n2vv6a">32</xref> time has
                not treated the Strasbourg map kindly: the outline is mutilated because someone cut
                off the corners at the bottom of both sides. Crude pin holes at the periphery show
                unsophisticated tacking and rough use, while water damage and mold renders many
                names difficult or impossible to read. For some time the skin lay, not rolled, but
                folded – while still damp. Evidence for this are red smudges near Florence which
                match mirror-image counterparts of heavily smeared red inscriptions for Perugia and
                Orvieto, which have become nearly unreadable as a result.</p>
            <p id="skj3bnkj4ea8">What the Strasbourg shares with the Cotton is a ‘flat’ hierarchy of
                little difference in the vignettes’ rendering of ordinary towns and important
                cities: the more important ones are only marginally larger and only slightly more
                elaborate in detail. This might indicate a similar restraint on their common source
                (or mutual copying past).</p>
            <p id="o0gest2eir668">The Cotton shows the complete peninsula and is of superior
                craftsmanship. This leads to the question where was the lower third – essentially
                the territory of the Kingdom of Naples? The River Tronto forms, in a certain sense
                on both maps, the frontier between central and southern Italy. After 1272, it was
                the southern border of the March of Ancona under papal control with the Duchy of
                Abruzzo, part of the Kingdom of Sicily until the nineteenth century.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref> It is not difficult to demonstrate a sudden
                shift in scale on the Cotton using the locations of 21 river mouths into the
                Adriatic south of Rimini. On these rocky shores, estuaries do not move position over
                the course of just one millennium, in contrast to swampy areas, which may.</p>
            <fig id="pmflhjs942df" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 5.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Plotting the distance on the map along the coastline in centimetres
                        against the distance on land in kilometres gives a local scale. The
                        discontinuity near Fermo indicates that two dissimilar images of different
                        scale were patched together.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_05.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_05.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="h9572bpb2njl">Down to the River Chienti, a scale of approximately 1:600,000 (= 6
                kilometers/centimeter) prevails which characterizes the scale used to map northern
                    Italy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref> After this come three estuaries
                at an artificially compressed scale which runs until the Tronto, after which further
                southwards a scale of approximately 1:900,000 (= 9 kilometers/centimeter) is used
                until the mouth of the Tiber.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref> This regional
                scale-change of the Cotton is unique among contemporary maps. However, shifting
                scales are a well-known feature of portolan charts, where some parts, say the Black
                Sea, have an orientation and size that are different to those of the Mediterranean,
                and so on.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref> All this happens precisely where
                the Strasbourg ends, and this is significant. The outline of the southern part of
                the peninsula on the Cotton is appreciably slimmer than its northern part. Had the
                mapmaker decided to continue with the ‘northern scale’, the entire peninsula would
                have required an additional 33 centimeters or so in space, resulting in a total
                height of 170 centimeters. One might speculate that, in view of the expenses already
                incurred, another half-sheet would likely not have mattered much. However, given the
                idea that is basically suggested in the accompanying text, of uniting Italy under
                the leadership of Venice,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref> it perhaps came in
                handy that the Kingdom of Naples was expertly ‘shrunk’.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn38">38</xref></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-i8dm03hs99" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>4. A Visual Comparison of the Outlines of Italy</title>
            <p id="g3zz3piaoljj">In this section, I argue that the two maps are of the same size by
                discussing the outlines of the peninsula. This differentiates the pair from many
                other ‘copies’ of fifteenth century maps. As far as I know, there are few direct
                copies of fifteenth century maps.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">39</xref></p>
            <fig id="nf4ehn8123zg" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 6.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>The outline of the Strasbourg map in black is superposed on the Cotton is
                        best fitted by a clockwise rotation by 3 degrees. Note that the Strasbourg
                        is more "sketchy", for instance by omitting the Venetian lagoon
                        completely.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_06.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_06.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="nrd4dh41i5g">The first sign that both maps share a common data set stems from
                comparing the contours of Italy. Milanesi already notes that both maps look very
                much the same, so that the Strasbourg “appears as a bad copy or a poor
                    relative”.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">40</xref> Although all portolan charts
                tend to share a similar general appearance, differences in the details abound. This
                is also true in the case of the Cotton (which at 140 x 66 centimeters is made up of
                two skins glued together, of approximately 66.5 x 68 centimeters and 66.5 x 71
                centimeters respectively) and the Strasbourg (65 x 95 centimeters, a single sheet).
                In keeping with a well-known method in philological studies, where questions arise
                as to what extent author A depended on author B or simply plagiarized content and
                meaning, one pores over maps for similarities and distinctions/marks of innovation.
                With the passing of time, however, the comparison is not always easy. In this
                section, I look at external agents influencing a more detailed comparison of the two
                artifacts. In the case of maps and their scaling, the predominant concern is of
                course shrinkage and warping of animal skins over 600 years. Albeit largely
                irrelevant in other medieval documents, in the case of maps these factors must be
                addressed in context, although such factors are difficult to quantify as they are
                heavily dependent on largely unknown historic storage conditions.</p>
            <p id="p9ii28y91yp5">Peter Mesenburg reports of warping of circles with an approximately
                29 centimeter radius on contemporary portolan charts in the millimeter region.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">41</xref> Shrinkage is of more concern, however,
                because after 600 years, lines rarely remain straight or at right angles: the Cotton
                has a two-millimeter-wide red frame just inside its outer edge. While the upper and
                lower boundaries run flush within a one millimeter margin, the vertical boundaries
                are indeed warped. The left margin (Adriatic side) deviates by ± eight millimeters
                from a straight line, the right margin (Tyrrhenian side) by even more. Hence, the
                width of the map between the red boundaries varies, starting with 63 centimeters at
                the top and (irregularly) increasing to 65.6 centimeters at the bottom. Assuming
                that the freshly drawn document really did have parallel vertical borders, shrinkage
                appears to have increased from the top (i.e., the outer layer when rolled?) to the
                bottom by 26 millimeters. From the fiducial marks, we can tell this number also
                includes, of course, warping by a (barely noticeable) pin-cushion distortion in the
                photographs and other errors made during the reproduction process and digital
                display. A tendency of more shrinkage toward the upper end is possibly connected to
                the differential drying of the outermost layer(s) when rolled. Compared to other
                similar documents, the Cotton appears to have been stored as a roll (hence its
                superior readability) and generally enjoyed careful handling during use. It should
                be noted, however, that a physical inspection of the original may alter some of the
                above measurements slightly.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">42</xref></p>
            <p id="s17y41c4hqik">For the Strasbourg, we have the unique opportunity to quantify
                distortions with the help of the superimposed portolan-like grid lines, presumably
                conceived and drawn parallel and at right angles as intended. Inspecting <xref
                    ref-type="fig" rid="bl8akf0wn9j">fig. 4</xref>, we see a number of rectangular
                grids of variable widths which during their genesis were (presumably) intended to be
                at right angles and rotated by 22.5 degrees, as required. Close analysis of the grid
                indeed reveals differential shrinking of the parchment. Assuming an originally
                regular quadratic design of the system of rhumb lines (see the ■ markings) and
                comparing them to the actual stars (x markings in the figure) reveals increasing
                distortion toward the upper-left corner of the map with up to one centimeter
                mismatch. The overall size of the deformation is similar to that of the Cotton but
                the pattern suggests more of a warping than the shrinkage of the Cotton. The
                corollary is of course a uniform or homogenous shrinkage of the Cotton roll
                depending on the distance of the ■ markings to the map margin, which cannot be
                tested in the same unique way as for the red border of the Cotton. However, it is
                reasonable to assume, considering the greater care the Cotton received over the
                centuries.</p>
            <fig id="bd8td9ngbj0n" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 7.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>A (simplified) rendering of the shrinkage documented in the Strasbourg
                        map via its superimposed grid image.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_07.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_07.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="djeyj7g9v9qo">To summarize, we do thus have a ‘component of mismatch’ up to the
                order of one centimeter which is independent of the cartographic intent and graphic
                ability of the mapmakers and occasioned by the passage of time. It correlates well
                with the overall (mis-)matching results.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">43</xref>
                Hence, supporting the assumption, we have two independent findings of a relatively
                more severe mismatch on the Adriatic and the estimated average distortion of the
                Strasbourg based on a reasonable model for the original design of the map. The
                visually excellent match of the coastlines is subject to (small) distortions which
                were not present when both maps were made. The next section presents a number of
                additional differences of interest between the two maps.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-uploxpwyrj" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>5. Other Differences between the Two Maps</title>
            <p id="fi1kypx159xg">Which map is the copy of the other and which is the original? Both
                remain open questions. As already noted, the coastal outline of the Strasbourg is
                much simpler compared to the finely detailed inlets and promontories of the Cotton.
                This increased local content would suggest the Cotton is the original. In this
                context, if both depend on a primary (unknown) source, the Cotton appears a ‘higher
                resolution’ copy.</p>
            <p id="ib7qbvbq5oiq">The next clue comes from the fact that a good match is obtained by
                rotating the Strasbourg map by three degrees in a clockwise direction, as shown in
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nf4ehn8123zg">fig. 6</xref>.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn44">44</xref> As both maps have a similar sheet width of 65 centimeters,
                this leads to insufficient coverage at the Istrian end of each map. Remarkably, the
                remaining maximum differences between the two contours after optimizing their match
                are still about a centimeter or less. As both measurements are randomly distributed,
                they neither cancel out nor compensate the ‘fuzziness’ of the coordinate matching,
                but in fact tend to increase it somewhat.</p>
            <p id="drqkey9vn1li">The actual coastline from Genoa to Latium is carefully depicted and
                well matched for both maps except at both ends. In the Levante region, the coastline
                on the Strasbourg stops at Albenga (illegible because written into the sea but well
                defined by comparison with the Cotton). Inspection at high resolution shows that the
                pale green wash indicating seawater first forms a non-existing promontory and then
                departs at right angles to the coast, although until this arbitrary excursion it had
                curiously followed the (secondary) Torrente Aroscia closely, before the latter flows
                into the Tyrrhenian Sea at Albenga. This strange or arbitrary ‘coastline’ is
                verifiably continued up to the settlement of Mendatica, documented at precisely the
                same location on the Cotton and located next to the border with France. As far as I
                know, neither Albenga nor the small stream had a significant function in any
                historically documented regional treaties, wars, or border disputes.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">45</xref></p>
            <p id="l7e3lgryx6cr">The reason for this deviation from the coastline on the Strasbourg
                is entirely unclear but similar to another deliberate departure at right angles from
                the coastline which is observed at Latium. There, the end of the excellent fit is
                reached at an unknown spot marked “gulorai” which on the Cotton is the last point
                before the port of Fiumicino at the mouth of the Tiber.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn46">46</xref> Beyond that point, the coastline of the Strasbourg map
                shows a right-angle trajectory out to sea which is, of course, contrary to ground
                truth, for the coast in fact continues straight on and forms the triangular
                protrusion seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nf4ehn8123zg">fig. 6</xref> and <xref
                    ref-type="fig" rid="bd8td9ngbj0n">fig. 7</xref>. Close inspection reveals that
                the thin preparatory tracing line does indeed continue out to sea, thus forming part
                of the original design. Therefore, the unrealistic right-angle bend of the coast was
                meant to signal the end of the studied area. These curious deviations from ‘standard
                practice’ may shed light on the mindset (one might say ‘mental map’) or intent of
                the mapmaker(s). One likely explanation could again be that it reflects a
                brouillon-type action signaling to a subsequent user the immediate end of reasonably
                ascertained knowledge. However, this speculation would have the Strasbourg adopt the
                role of precursor rather than plagiarist, without any further evidence to
                substantiate such a claim.</p>
            <p id="j44mijhqnrbd">As to the coastline in the lower left-hand corner of the map (i.e.,
                northeast Italy), there is no trace of the Venetian Lagoon in the upper Adriatic and
                the easternmost readable city is “exol”/Jesolo on an untraced coastline marked only
                by the green color of the sea to the northeastern end of the map. Again this may be
                interpreted as an unnecessarily subtle detail in an already well-known territory or
                as a sign of negligent tracing during hasty copying. At the upper end (i.e.,
                southeast Italy) beyond Fermo, the mapmaker appears to have simply joined the end of
                the animal skin with a haphazard stroke which does not reflect the passage of the
                real coastline. This implies that he had reached the neck of the animal skin and,
                with it, the limits of his map’s area coverage. It occurs at the same height as and
                is similar to the turn-off in the Tyrrhenian Sea. Also, no settlement above Fermo is
                marked out and the ‘neck’ is left empty, except for Rome. Apparently the mapmaker
                originally planned to cut off the neck of the skin at that level and was thereby
                willing to scarify the Rome vignette which thus only serves a ‘placeholder’ function
                as a landmark. This would in turn explain the noticeable scale-change between Lecco
                and Arezzo (approximately seven kilometers/centimeter), when compared to the
                distance between Arezzo and Rome (approximately nine kilometers/centimeter), as
                noted by Grenacher. Strasbourg’s Rome is located at the same place as on the Cotton,
                already implementing the scale-shift from northern to southern Italy.</p>
            <p id="nex5zdooubs8">We have no evidence that the mapmaker intended such a continuation
                into southern Italy and a reasonable estimate for the rectangular part of the skin
                (minus the neck) is 65 x 81 centimeters, which just about covers the carefully
                copied parts. To summarize, the coastline at all four corners of the map was left
                undetermined, thus reinforcing the sense of a ‘work in progress’. However, the
                overall bad condition of the skin, with tears, nail holes, and missing parts, makes
                it equally likely that the project was abandoned at a rather late stage.</p>
            <p id="npsmdnzdizz">More generally, the detailed comparison of the outlines of the
                peninsula shows that the Strasbourg map cannot be a copy (or certainly at least not
                a careful copy) of the Cotton and cannot have served as a cartographic source for
                the Cotton, at least when considering the outlines of rivers and streams. The
                following sections present three separate regional studies focusing on extended
                objects like rivers and lakes and their toponym inventory. The aim here was to
                elucidate what could have happened during the elaboration of the two documents.</p>
            <p id="orh3oz6vtbdc">Beyond differences in contouring or geometrical placement, and the
                ensuing differences in geographical information density, there are other structural
                elements that differ between the two maps which merit further study. One important
                item on this list is the visual communication of ‘importance’, in other words, the
                ranking of Italian places of significance. Biondo searches for and glorifies the
                ancestry of historic sites, but what about his contemporaries, the two makers of our
                maps?</p>
            <p id="w3ysq6ii8xbe">As shown above, there is little hierarchy expressed through graphic
                mark-making: lapis lazuli is applied randomly and only two-portcullis vignettes are
                a sign of ‘importance’ on the Cotton. In contrast, the Strasbourg transfers another
                element from portolan charts to its inland design: rubrication of place names. On
                average, about every fifth entry or so in these charts is rendered in red, many of
                them without reflecting any particular merit in our modern understanding but
                generally denoting ‘significance’. The relevant numbers for our maps are compared
                below in <xref ref-type="table" rid="i1q5qy5j4iac">Table. 1</xref>.</p>
            <table-wrap id="i1q5qy5j4iac">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Statistics on the Content of the Two Maps<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47"
                            >47</xref></title>
                </caption>
                <table id="tbl-qcu6nurazcbd" frame="box" rules="rows" cellpadding="5">
                    <colgroup>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                        <col/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Cotton</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>%</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Strasbourg</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>%</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total vignettes</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>1220</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>649</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>53.2</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Total important vignettes</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>104</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>8.5</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>95</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14.6</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>On common site</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>937</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>649</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>69.3</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Missing</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>12</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>278</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>42.8</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Important towns therein</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>62</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>6.6</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>95</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>14.6</p></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Agree</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>55</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>76</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>55</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Disagree</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>7</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>11</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>40</p></td>
                            <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p/></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p id="r7xxqprxso5x">The Strasbourg retains only about 70 percent of the entries in the
                Cotton but has a much larger percentage of important towns and only twelve entries
                which do not appear in the Cotton. The distribution of these ‘political statements’
                is interesting. Only seven two-portcullis names are not rubricated and four of those
                are missing entirely: Spoleto, Todi, Ostia, and Tivoli. Toscanello and Montefiascone
                are normal vignettes, and Asti in Piedmont is marked but unnamed, hence could not be
                rubricated. Thus overall concordance on the importance of two-portcullis sites is
                good. Among these, we have (of course, one might say) the important places like
                Rome, Florence, Pisa, Milan, and so on but there are also notable omissions. More
                importantly, north of the River Po, where the Cotton only has nine distinguished
                cities, the Strasbourg has eighteen rubricated entries – twice the number. Clearly,
                there must have been a different understanding of ‘importance’ – and this alone
                merits further study in future.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gmsymw" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>6. The Mutilation(?) of the Strasbourg Map</title>
            <fig id="k0ujxfn3kh9m" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 8.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>This small excerpt of the Strasbourg map shows the ragged lower edge in
                        the vicinity of the river Oglio. The Vignette of Daleng fits into a 3 x 4 mm
                        rectangle. The dark band at the edge is taken as an indication that the cut
                        was deliberate.</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_08.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_08.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="h8tmmrp42nyt">We have seen that one probably needed three sheets of (readily)
                available animal skin to render Italy at the scale of 1:600,000, as used in the
                Strasbourg map. Hence for a general survey map, the sheet-size of 65 x 95
                centimeters is insufficient in width and, of course, in height, too, but more than
                that, the image of the Alpine region is severely abridged and has been strangely
                mutilated, as evidenced by its ragged edges. However, there is some evidence
                suggesting that the northeastern corner may have been already removed during the
                inscription phase. As shown in high resolution, the ragged cut was apparently made
                along a trace line marked in the same color as the river markings. The name of San
                Bartolomeo appears to have been squeezed into the margin <italic>after</italic> the
                removal of the missing part. The pale green ink along the rim otherwise serves to
                emphasize rivers and lakes. But here it was apparently used to delineate the
                cut.</p>
            <p id="ms6mq812ss4e">Intriguingly, all this happens at the headwaters of the
                “olium”/Oglio river and up to San Bartolomeo on the Passo del Tonale. For centuries
                up to the present day, this little-known pass has marked the border between Italian
                Lombardy and German-speaking Trentino. The missing part depicts what in the Cotton
                is the Val Telline (Valtellina) – a pass that was heavily contested over the
                centuries between, on the one hand, northern powers that would (much later) coalesce
                into the Swiss Confederation and, on the other, the various powers that ruled over
                centuries in Lombardy.</p>
            <p id="i0161a70zt9ol">The next deliberate removal of part of the animal skin is only
                identifiable through a comparison with the Cotton and clearly happens at the
                confluence of the Adige (German: Etsch, marked on the map as “f. addax”) and the
                Torrente Noce from the Val di Non which descends from the Passo del Tonale described
                above. Again, the brutal cut follows a marking and, although undecipherable, the two
                vignettes facing each other across the river at this point are readily identified on
                the Cotton by the label “mez” (modern Mezzocorona/Kronmetz) and “conigsperg”
                (modern-day castello di Monreale/Königsberg, near Salorno).<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="tvsd9r1zwrib">48</xref> And again, for centuries these two sites
                traditionally marked the southern border of German-speaking South Tyrol and
                Trentino, in other words between essentially Hapsburg dominions and Venetian
                ambitions. The deliberate cut crosses the Adige/Etsch at the last (now-illegible)
                entry identified on the Cotton as “formiga”/Frangart just five kilometers south of
                Bolzano/Bozen at the confluence of the Eisack and Etsch. Here ends the dark blue
                border marking the removal of the northeastern part of the skin. The cut itself ends
                just north of Bressanone/Brixen, exactly where the Cotton ends. Further evidence for
                a deliberate ‘mutilation’ or elision of the northeastern corner is manifest in the
                coastal stretch northeast of Venice. The same dark greenish marking appears to
                suggest deliberate removal. Further on toward the coast, the (indistinct) coastline
                of the Adria runs toward the upper-right edge.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="uahbh522xhfm"
                    >49</xref> The last readable entries before the ‘border’ marked in blue are the
                three settlements of “ouerzo”/Oderzo, “bufoleo”/?, and “cauclan”/Cavolano on the
                Livenza river. However, this border does not, as far as I know, represent a border
                separating languages.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="i7tp6qqyvn0g">50</xref> Why would the
                mapmaker literally cut off the Friuli?</p>
            <p id="g2pz0yunufiu">On the other hand, both maps are clearly ‘non-political’, in that
                they have neither boundaries nor territorial labels or markers, and only indicate
                settlements, rivers, and the coast. A more mundane explanation for the mutilations
                could be that they are the remnants of a rescue attempt to halt further
                deterioration through rot, without linguistic or political connotations. The
                coincidence with boundaries would then have happened by chance alone, a possibility
                that Marica Milanesi, after closer consultation with me on this matter,
                suggests.</p>
            <p id="z4nqhfq02a4a">On the French-speaking side, a narrow strip has also been removed.
                The tell-tale green marker is also present, suggesting that the strip was removed
                purposefully and that the map was not subject to a random act of vandalism. The
                prominently ‘saved’ feature is the source lake of the River Po, which all the
                relevant maps<xref ref-type="fn" rid="kinxkucfdme">51</xref> retain, and the cut
                follows the Alpine watershed, as does the modern-day border between France and
                Italy. The rest is difficult to read even with the help of the Cotton as a
                cross-reference for designations. It is subsequently too early to draw any
                conclusions. Specialists in minority and relict languages can perhaps better shed
                light on these suppositions. It is my personal belief that the unprecedented
                richness, diversity, and local precision of both maps may help other relevant
                investigations into early fifteenth-century thinking.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-pq31jqqi0k" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>7. The Rendering of Swamp Areas</title>
            <p id="wv4ush1hxuc">Beyond pure location, a map uses numerous conventions and symbols to
                communicate meaning to the audience, among them coloring and shading of extended
                objects like islands or lakes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">52</xref> One example
                of such building blocks of what scholars call ‘map-based dialogue’ is an intriguing
                feature of the Cotton that distinguishes it from other maps of its time, namely the
                rendering of swamps with distinct graphic marks, quite different from those used to
                indicate lake surfaces. By comparison, the Strasbourg, for example, uses the same
                graphic marks for wetlands and lakes, making no distinction between the two.<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">53</xref> This is best seen in the Chiana Valley
                (Valdichiana) between Arezzo and “chiusi”, but other instances merit further
                study.</p>
            <fig id="uacvam0d85k6" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 9.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>The rendering of the Chiana valley side by side of the Cotton (left) and
                        the Strasbourg map (right).</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_09.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_09.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="yxlnp0x1vhab">The stippled surface is quite different from the wavelets
                representing lakes, such as nearby Lake Trasimeno.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54"
                    >54</xref> Other wetlands share this feature as well: the Maremma near Grosseto
                in Tuscany, the Valle Padusa northwest of Ravenna, and extensive wetlands around the
                Venetian Lagoon, extending from the Musone river to the “padus
                    ficariolo”/Ficarolo.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">55</xref> To Biondo, these
                places had significance, attested by his introduction to the territory of Venice
                which he describes succinctly in chapter 8.2, ‘Venice’: [T]he duchy is eighty miles
                long [...] The breadth of the region is variable, its only boundaries being the
                marshes formed by the waves of the sea, as they advance and recede toward and away
                from dry land.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">56</xref></p>
            <p id="kvltsh6wfwmp">Remarkably, the Pontine Marshes south of Rome and the Clanio
                marshland north of Naples are simply ignored, appearing to have no demarcation at
                all. However, other wetlands such as Lake Fucine and those between Rieti and Terni,
                which have survived into our time, as well as some periodically inundated areas in
                the lower Arno Valley between Lucca and Pisa, are shown with the regular lake
                    markings.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">57</xref></p>
            <p id="iqg3qqdfodlg">One may wonder why these areas warranted a special area symbol,
                foreshadowing the sophisticated graphic ‘special features’ which tremendously enrich
                the vocabulary of modern maps. The consequences of the neglect of Roman hydraulic
                engineering works were dramatic, as, starting in the early tenth century, much
                traffic moved over to neighboring Val d’Elsa (Via Francigena) which then grew in
                political importance. However, despite flooding, the Chiana was still used for
                transport, as is shown by the following source:</p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p id="x4z700xjurv9">In the past, the hills of Chiuso (between Cortona, Valiano, and
                    Foiano) were equipped, due to their strategic position, with castles and ports,
                    albeit rudimentary, for the landing of boats in service on the Chiana. The name
                    of “Il porto” remains today in the cases of Farneta, Cignano, Fasciano,
                    Bettolle, Creti, Foiano, and Cesa. The port of Farneta is a neighbor of the port
                    of Foiano della Chiana [...].<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">58</xref></p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p id="nhnopywnfkvc">On the other hand, the Chiana wetlands were the theater of intense
                military struggles between Guelph Florence, Ghibelline Siena/Arezzo, and the Papal
                States until 1492, when the Medici took control of Tuscany.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn59">59</xref> In the heavily contested territory, the marshlands (and
                indeed knowledge of their whereabouts) may have come in handy.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn60">60</xref> This area symbol thus may have had a military significance
                for the map’s readers.</p>
            <p id="d3yf7ojja38l">The topic of marshland markings distinguished from lake markings is
                apparently also taken up by Nicolaus Germanus in his <italic>Italia Moderna</italic>
                of 1467<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">61</xref> and in Leonardo da Vinci’s
                    <italic>Map of Tuscany and Chiana Valley</italic> of circa 1503–1506,<xref
                    ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">62</xref> which denotes marshy areas in a lighter blue.
                The use of such area symbols in all these maps indicates that the (educated) public
                – the mapmakers’ patrons and clients – were aware of such subtle cartographic
                signals and suggests a sophisticated appreciation of semiotic features.</p>
            <p id="jcabayj5m3ns">To summarize, the topic of special area symbols for marshland is a
                recurring style element in early mapping and perhaps one of the earliest (surviving)
                examples is found in the Cotton. For unknown reasons, the maker of the Strasbourg
                chose not to retain it, one assumption again being that the natural environments of
                such wetlands were known to its immediate users and thus did not warrant the extra
                effort, as was the case with the missing place names in known territory (see
                below).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-ngyve6h59y" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>8. A Common Source?</title>
            <p id="ziv3i2h1gu9m">Further detailed comparison of the two maps shows that their
                similarities betray a common source, but with neither being an outright copy, either
                way. The idea does not rest only on the common overall size, but is also supported
                by two observations: common idiosyncrasies or errors on the one hand and distinct
                details in particular. Both maps share the banana-shaped outline of the swamp of the
                Valdichiana but the real Chiana wetlands extended only from “ulmo”/Ripa di Olmo
                (where the canal was later dug) to “clusi”/Chiusi on a straight north-south
                orientation. The bend toward the east (toward the left in <xref ref-type="fig"
                    rid="uacvam0d85k6">fig. 9</xref>) follows the course of the Chiana through hilly
                terrain toward “orbiuato”/Orvieto but without the extended wetlands suggested by our
                two maps. Hence, the banana-shape appears unique to a particular rendering or rather
                misreading of a common source.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">63</xref> By
                comparison, Germanus’s and Da Vinci’s Valdichiana are pretty straight.</p>
            <p id="qrjly1mbhjm">The outlines of extended objects (rivers and lakes) reveal a
                free-hand style of draftsmanship common to both the Cotton and Strasbourg. A typical
                example is Lake Trasimeno: all settlements are present, but the size and orientation
                of the oval are quite different. Note also the simplified outline of the swamps in
                the Strasbourg, which, within a margin of one to two centimeters, follow those of
                the Cotton – not bad for a manuscript map 60 x 100 centimeters in size!</p>
            <p id="jzyq27jvymxg">The toponym inventory has a high degree of common places, albeit
                often with different spellings and selection. For instance, Cortona (494 meters
                    ASL)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">64</xref> sits high above the valley floor
                and to the side, as shown in both maps. Below it, at the shoreline, the Cotton has
                the settlement of “cam?ia”/Camucia, whereas Strasbourg instead marks out “a
                zingolo”/?, which may possibly represent nearby Monsigliolo (Camucia-Monsigliolo;
                273 meters ASL). Next to these sites, the Cotton has a “castel d’lapena” which
                cannot be identified, whereas Strasbourg displays a “castel dalla plane”. In the
                area of Tuscany (for which high-resolution digital images taken from both maps are
                available) other examples include the entry “bolsena” on the Cotton which becomes
                “Bolgena” on the Strasbourg, while “toscanello” becomes “Toschanela”, and
                “vicarello” and “anguillara” similarly lose an “l” on the Strasbourg, and so on. The
                lettering evidently holds many potential clues and perhaps paleolinguistic and
                paleographic studies of the name forms will provide further insights into the origin
                and/or makers of these exceptional charts.</p>
            <p id="od2xneskar4t">A strikingly similar geographical lapse can be found at Lake Lugano
                where nine toponyms and the outline of the lake are squeezed into an area of only 3
                x 4 centimeters. Here the characteristic U-shape of the lower half of the lake is
                faithfully reproduced by both maps but the upper-right half of the real lake to the
                northeast of Lugano is missing in both renderings. This clearly demonstrates their
                dependence on a similar (or same) source which also carried this inaccurate
                information. More detailed study is bound to unearth yet more telling examples but
                the message seems clear (to me): underlying these two maps is a common source.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-f51ar3fpk6" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>9. The Coastline in <italic>Liguria</italic></title>
            <p id="hpns30moba4s">Having dealt with inland sections, a third detailed comparison
                deals with (part of) of the extensive littoral outline and hydrologic network of the
                two maps. Here, I choose the layout and marked settlements along a
                115-kilometer-long stretch of the Ligurian and Tuscan coast between Portofino and
                Pisa.</p>
            <fig id="igq5jgxi81q4" fig-type="content-image">
                <label>Figure 10.</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Comparison of the coast and rivers between Pisa and Portofino of the
                        Cotton (on top) and the Strasbourg map (below).</title>
                </caption>
                <alternatives>

                    <graphic specific-use="online"
                        xlink:href="https://hertz-foto-os1.biblhertz.it/iiif/3/dpub%2Fhsah0104%2Fhsah_0104_10.jp2/full/max/0/default.jpg"/>
                    <graphic specific-use="archival" xlink:href="hsah_0104_10.jpg"/>
                </alternatives>
            </fig>
            <p id="gtn4c61g96vi">The distance from Pisa to Portofino (116 kilometers) is shown by
                the straight line which is 15.2 centimeters long.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65"
                    >65</xref> First the coastline will be discussed and then the placement of the
                rivers compared.</p>
            <p id="qwiqrfdx2xa">The bight of Portofino is not rendered accurately because in reality
                it already ends at Chiavari, the next marked point on both maps. This suggests that
                a verbal description of the coastline may have inspired the deep recess, whereas the
                bight running from Portovenere to La Spezia (“larexa”/Lerici) shows a fair degree of
                fidelity to ground truth. In between and beyond Sestri Levante (marked on both
                maps), the Strasbourg gives a schematic representation of the five equidistant
                vignettes of the Cinque Terre communities (not all named), whereas the Cotton
                clearly faces problems fitting and naming them in the space available. Apart from
                this, there is concordance as to the estuaries and the general curvature of the
                coast in both maps. In the hinterland, Sarzana, Lucca, and Pisa are each marked with
                two portcullises on the Cotton, whereas the Strasbourg assigns Chiavari distinctive
                red lettering. Starting with the Arno river, crossing Pisa, one immediately sees
                that the actual rendering of the river courses is largely dependent on the space
                available between the differently sized but accurately placed vignettes with, I
                believe, one significant exception: whenever a tributary reaches a main river or a
                river reaches the sea, their locations match. At least to the craftsmen of both maps
                executing the drawing, these geographical places held a significance, which is also
                attested by the numerous vignettes nestled in the confluences. These afford place
                recognition, confirming at least three elements and their relation to local space:
                river A flows into river B at town C.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">66</xref> In a
                sense, they provide spatial clues similar to promontories in portolan charts:
                direction from place A to B changes into the new direction from B to C at B. The
                continuation of the zig-zagging or curving lines further into the interior is
                subsequently subject to less stringent rules and accuracy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="import-dqyb6h9ygc" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>11. Conclusion</title>
            <p id="nk2284jso3o">As an image, the Cotton appears to follow the same principles that
                guided Biondo in structuring his narration of the <italic>Italia
                Illustrata</italic>. It ‘illuminates’ Italy from the Alpine Arc to the Ionian Sea
                and excludes the islands to form a single, magnificent unity, not the three-partite
                political structure of its day. It also applies the ancient technique of patterning
                the subsets of data along the rivers, just as Strabo did. And, finally, it even
                shares with Biondo’s work the relative paucity and incompleteness of information in
                the region of the Kingdom of Sicily. But there the similarities end. Despite
                containing 1200-plus toponyms, the interior plotting is very different from Biondo’s
                account, which features 2000-plus place names<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67"
                    >67</xref> see also (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Guckelsberger.2022"
                    >Guckelsberger/Geus </xref> in this volume). Obviously, the Cotton and Biondo
                share the noteworthy cities, the <italic>poleis episemoi</italic>, but the
                distribution of the other settlements differs locally. As such, we can come to the
                conclusion that the Cotton was certainly not Biondo’s source but, perhaps, Biondo
                did see the map at some point, somewhere in northern Italy, and it might have
                inspired his literary write-up of a general survey purely in words. Also, Biondo’s
                desire to resurrect Antiquity and its splendor has very little to do with the
                Venetians’ detailed information on trade routes, military intelligence, and
                administrative knowledge of the various powers which the Cotton so clearly
                    demonstrates.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">68</xref> They are, to me, two views
                of the same entity: an illustrated and indeed <italic>illustrious</italic> Italy
                seen from different perspectives.</p>
            <p id="gqlukxdl98j9">The existence of such extensive pre-modern maps of Italy firmly
                argues against the notion that Italian cartography developed rapidly after the
                discovery of Ptolemy’s <italic>Geography</italic>: it was already emerging
                independently of his great legacy. The crossover from portolan charts to terrestrial
                maps of similar ‘precision’ is impressively documented by the two specimens
                discussed here. Indeed, Milanesi has already diagnosed the relative similarity
                between them to a lost or unknown prototype.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="vk9b01zupo9"
                    >69</xref> Furthermore, their widely different cartographic languages argue for
                a vigorous program or at least clear awareness of the cartographic requirements yet
                to be developed in subsequent centuries. After all, both maps are the earliest
                surviving attempts at a constructed landmap as evidenced by the portolan-like
                overlay. I believe in two master-maps, one for northern and central Italy and
                another for the Kingdom of Naples. The Strasbourg may even have been nearer to a
                source map (or be a copy thereof), despite its poor graphics. (Indeed it may be a
                brouillon or a draft copy?). In the area covered by both maps, the Cotton has 1220
                names, while the Strasbourg contains only 649, at last count. Conversely, it has
                twelve names that do not appear on the Cotton and a clear case of alternate names in
                a sequence in the Chiana Valley demonstrates (among other things) independent or
                alternate input data.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">70</xref> The same applies for
                rivers. Such an exchange and correlation of nearby place names suggest that an
                itinerary-type data set was available from which one mapmaker chose one name and the
                other another. Of course, both mapmakers would have had additional information at
                their disposal and decided to add in or omit other points. Numerous variant
                spellings of the selfsame place names may well provide further clues on the
                relationship between the two artifacts. Clearly more examples are needed, but the
                case is now open.</p>
            <p id="e1qz8is5mat9">The overwhelming majority of details suggest a common source but
                different graphical dexterity or attention. Finely traced – and in detail superbly
                faithful – inlets and promontories on the Cotton suggest superior local knowledge,
                while the Strasbourg’s preparatory markings and penstrokes and factual but rather
                crude vignettes may signal a more technical ‘preliminary’, even preparatory stage of
                the same compilation. Furthermore, a study of the lettering by palaeographic experts
                would be a welcome approach to dating the document.</p>
            <p id="hy283cixc7mf">It seems likely that the master chart not only served Cotton and
                Strasbourg and Biondo, but also those mentioned below. (Indeed it would support,
                rather than contradict, the author’s argument.) In fact, in her article cited at the
                start, Milanesi writes that in 1999 Molly Bourne vehemently advocated the hypothesis
                that one of these maps, the Cotton, is somehow related to the wall map of Italy
                designed for the second time by Antonio Leonardi in the Palazzo Ducale in Venice
                after the fire of 1483 and continues in footnote 21 that Peter Barber in personal
                communication with her on the matter believes that the two maps may have had, at
                least, a common source, which seems to me more than possible.<xref ref-type="fn"
                    rid="fn71">71</xref> The Strasbourg may generally lack river names but not
                systematically. Without an extensive search, it appears to me that those names which
                    <italic>are</italic> given may have served as a means of quick orientation in
                answering practical questions like “Where are we at the moment?” either during the
                drafting of the map or during a copying process. For instance: there are six rivers
                issuing into the Adriatic Sea between Ravenna and Rimini and each one is named in
                the Cotton, but only the fifth is named in the Strasbourg. Nearby, a total of nine
                rivers flow into the Valle Padusa between Bologna and the coast. On the Cotton they
                are named and simply stop at the edge of the stippled area, whereas on the
                Strasbourg, they namelessly merge into a lake, but, again, only the next to last is
                named. More study is surely needed here.</p>
            <p id="wiycpcloc6o">Finally, it is unclear whether the imaginary boundary from Ostia to
                the River Tronto was a political, linguistic, or cultural watershed. The Tronto was
                indeed for many centuries the southern limit of the March of Ancona, whether under
                Langobardian, Carolingian, or Angevin rule. Note also that the earliest map of the
                whole of peninsular Italy,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">72</xref> the bisected map
                of Italy by Fra Paolino, continues its northern half down to the Gargano Peninsula
                so that this terminus cannot be considered a fixture of historic geography.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="_rk0n" sec-type="chapter">
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p id="i42joir">Numerous discussions with Marica Milanesi, Nathalie Bouloux, Peter
                Baber, and P.D.A. Harvey helped shape this project.</p>
            <p id="qkyk7xg5r2jj">Thanks also to Lance Anderson for editing assistance.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="Almagia.1929">
                <label>Almagià 1929</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Almagià</surname>
                            <given-names>Roberto</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1929</year>
                    <article-title>Monumenta Italiae Cartographica. Riproduzione Di Carte Generali e
                        Regionali d’Italia Dal Secolo XIV al XVII Raccolte e
                        Illustrate</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="BennetDurand.1952">
                <label>Bennet Durand 1952</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Bennet Durand</surname>
                            <given-names>Dana</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1952</year>
                    <article-title>The Vienna-Klosterneuburg Map Corpus of the Fifteenth Century: A
                        Study in the Transition from Medieval to Modern Science</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Biondo.2005b">
                <label>Biondo 2005b</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Biondo</surname>
                            <given-names>Flavio</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>White</surname>
                            <given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Italy Illuminated: Books I-IV</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Biondo.2016">
                <label>Biondo 2016</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Biondo</surname>
                            <given-names>Flavio</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>White</surname>
                            <given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2016</year>
                    <article-title>Italy Illuminated: Books V-VIII</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Bourne.1999">
                <label>Bourne 1999</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Bourne</surname>
                            <given-names>Molly</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Francesco II Gonzaga and Maps as Palace Decoration in Renaissance
                        Mantua</article-title>
                    <source>Imago mundi. The Journal of the International Society for the History of
                        Cartography</source>
                    <volume>69</volume>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1080/03085699908592903</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Briguglia.2017">
                <label>Briguglia 2017</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Briguglia</surname>
                            <given-names>Gianluca</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2017</year>
                    <article-title>Dante a Strasburgo</article-title>
                    <source>Il Post</source>
                    <uri
                        xlink:href="https://www.ilpost.it/gianlucabriguglia/2017/04/10/dante-a-strasburgo/"
                        >https://www.ilpost.it/gianlucabriguglia/2017/04/10/dante-a-strasburgo/</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Cacheyjr.2018">
                <label>Cachey Jr. 2018</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Cachey Jr.</surname>
                            <given-names>Theodore J.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2018</year>
                    <article-title>La mappa d’Italia in Dante, Petrarca e Boccaccio</article-title>
                    <source>Le tre corone. Rivista internazionale di studi su Dante, Petrarca e
                        Boccaccio</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.19272/201812101002</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Campbell.2011">
                <label>Campbell 2011</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="web-page">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Campbell</surname>
                            <given-names>Tony</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2011</year>
                    <article-title>Census of Pre-Sixteenth-Century Portolan Charts – Corrections and
                        Updates to the Article in Imago Mundi: International Journal for the History
                        of Cartography, 38 (1986)</article-title>
                    <uri xlink:href="https://www.maphistory.info/portolancensus.html"
                        >https://www.maphistory.info/portolancensus.html</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Campbell.2013">
                <label>Campbell 2013</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="web-page">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Campbell</surname>
                            <given-names>Tony</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2013</year>
                    <article-title>Red Names on the Portolan Charts (1311-1677): A Detailed
                        Investigation</article-title>
                    <uri xlink:href="https://www.maphistory.info/RedNamesCommentary.html"
                        >https://www.maphistory.info/RedNamesCommentary.html</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Commineau.1451">
                <label>Commineau 1451</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="manuscript">
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Commineau</surname>
                            <given-names>Hugues</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1451</year>
                    <article-title>Claudius Ptolomaeus, Cosmographia, Jacobus Angelus
                        interpres</article-title>
                    <uri xlink:href="https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc63677b"
                        >https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc63677b</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Dalche.1995">
                <label>Dalché 1995</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Dalché</surname>
                            <given-names>Patrick Gautier</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Carte marine et portulan au XIIe siècle: Le Liber de existencia
                        riueriarum et forma maris nostri Mediterranei (Pise, circa
                        1200)</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Dalche.1996">
                <label>Dalché 1996</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Dalché</surname>
                            <given-names>Patrick Gautier</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Pour une histoire du regard geographique: Conception et usage de
                        la carte au XVe siècle</article-title>
                    <source>Micrologus</source>
                    <volume>4</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Dalche.2005">
                <label>Dalché 2005</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Dalché</surname>
                            <given-names>Patrick Gautier</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Du Yorkshire à l’Inde: Une “Géographie” urbaine et maritime de la
                        fin du XIIe siècle</article-title>
                    <source>Hautes études médiévales et modernes</source>
                    <volume>89</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Domenico.2002">
                <label>Domenico 2002</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Domenico</surname>
                            <given-names>Roy Palmer</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>The Regions of Italy: A Reference Guide to History and
                        Culture</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Edson.2007">
                <label>Edson 2007</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Edson</surname>
                            <given-names>Evelyn</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>The World Map 1300-1492: The Persistence of Tradition and
                        Transformation</article-title>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1353/book.3516</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Grenacher.1948">
                <label>Grenacher 1948</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Grenacher</surname>
                            <given-names>Franz</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1948</year>
                    <article-title>Die vermutlich älteste Karte mit Darstellungen von Teilen des
                        Tessins</article-title>
                    <source>Jahresbericht der Geographischen Gesellschaft von Bern</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5169/seals-323083</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Guckelsberger.2022">
                <label>Guckelsberger/Geus 2022</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Guckelsberger</surname>
                            <given-names>Kurt</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Geus</surname>
                            <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>

                    <year>2022</year>
                    <article-title>Measurements, Maps, and Other Source Material in Biondo’s Italia
                        Illustrata: The Example of Latium</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Michalsky</surname>
                            <given-names>Tanja</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thiering</surname>
                            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Walking through history. An Interdisciplinary Approach to Flavio
                        Biondo’s Spaces in the Italia Illustrata</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48431/hsah.0103</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Harvey.1980">
                <label>Harvey 1980</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Harvey</surname>
                            <given-names>Paul D. A.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1980</year>
                    <article-title>The History of Topographical Maps, Symbols, Pictures and
                        Surveys</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Harvey.1987">
                <label>Harvey 1987</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Harvey</surname>
                            <given-names>Paul D. A.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>

                    <year>1987</year>
                    <article-title>Local and Regional Cartography in Medieval Europe</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Harley</surname>
                            <given-names>John Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Woodward</surname>
                            <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Cartography in Prehistoric, Ancient, and Medieval Europe and the
                        Mediterranean</source>
                    <volume>1</volume>
                    <uri
                        xlink:href="https://press.uchicago.edu/books/HOC/HOC_V1/HOC_VOLUME1_chapter20.pdf"
                        >https://press.uchicago.edu/books/HOC/HOC_V1/HOC_VOLUME1_chapter20.pdf</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Harvey.1991">
                <label>Harvey 1991</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Harvey</surname>
                            <given-names>Paul D. A.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1991</year>
                    <article-title>Medieval Maps</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="lilley">
                <label>Lilley/Millea/Vetch</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="web-page">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Lilley</surname>
                            <given-names>Keith D.</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Millea</surname>
                            <given-names>Nick</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Vetch</surname>
                            <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <article-title>Linguistic Geographies: Online research project, Kings College
                        London</article-title>
                    <uri xlink:href="http://www.goughmap.org/about/"
                        >http://www.goughmap.org/about/</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Melchior.2018">
                <label>Melchior 2018</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="web-page">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Melchior</surname>
                            <given-names>Luca</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2018</year>
                    <article-title>Varietà Romanze: Friuli</article-title>
                    <uri xlink:href="http://www.kit.gwi.uni-muenchen.de/?p=13160#26v=1">link</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Mesenburg.1986">
                <label>Mesenburg 1986</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Mesenburg</surname>
                            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1986</year>
                    <article-title>Rechner gestützte Analyse zum kartographischen und geodätischen
                        Informationsgehalt von Portolankarten</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Kretschmer</surname>
                            <given-names>Ingrid</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Kartographiehistorisches Kolloquium, Wien ’86</source>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Mesenburg.1990">
                <label>Mesenburg 1990</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Mesenburg</surname>
                            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1990</year>
                    <article-title>Untersuchungen zur kartometrischen Auswertung mittelalterlicher
                        Portolane</article-title>
                    <source>Kartographische Nachrichten</source>
                    <volume>40</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Meurer.1999">
                <label>Meurer 1999</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Meurer</surname>
                            <given-names>Peter H.</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>1999</year>
                    <article-title>Nicolaus Germanus</article-title>
                    <source>Neue Deutsche Biographie</source>
                    <uri
                        xlink:href="https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/pnd100955037.html#ndbcontent"
                        >https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/pnd100955037.html#ndbcontent</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Milanesi.2008">
                <label>Milanesi 2008</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Milanesi</surname>
                            <given-names>Marica</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Antico e moderno nella cartografia umanistica: Le grandi carte
                        d’Italia nel Quattrocento</article-title>
                    <source>Geographia Antiqua</source>
                    <volume>16–17</volume>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Milanesi.2022">
                <label>Milanesi 2022</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Milanesi</surname>
                            <given-names>Marica</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2022</year>
                    <article-title>I fiumi retici nelle carte dell’Italia tra XV e XVI secolo: Breve
                        storia di una rete impossibile</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Bouloux</surname>
                            <given-names>Nathalie</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Ducène</surname>
                            <given-names> Jean-Charles</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Territoires, régions, royaumes: Le développement d’une cartographie
                        régionale et locale dans l’Occident latin et le monde arabe (xe-xve
                        siècle)</source>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1484/M.CSM-EB.5.131065</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Mittenhuber.2009">
                <label>Mittenhuber/Klöti 2009</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Mittenhuber</surname>
                            <given-names>Florian</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Klöti</surname>
                            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Ptolemaios-Rezeption in der
                        Kartographiegeschichte</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Mittenhuber</surname>
                            <given-names>Florian</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Stückelberger</surname>
                            <given-names>Alfred</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Klaudios Ptolemaios Handbuch der Geographie: Ergänzungsband mit einer
                        Edition des Kanons bedeutender Städte</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>383</fpage>
                    <lpage>401</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Mittenhuber.2009b">
                <label>Mittenhuber 2009</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Mittenhuber</surname>
                            <given-names>Florian</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Falshe Breitenwerte und ihre Folgen</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Mittenhuber</surname>
                            <given-names>Florian</given-names>
                        </name><name>
                            <surname>Stückelberger</surname>
                            <given-names>Alfred</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <source>Klaudios Ptolemaios Handbuch der Geographie: Ergänzungsband mit einer
                        Edition des Kanons bedeutender Städte</source>
                    <volume>3</volume>
                    <fpage>245</fpage>
                    <lpage>252</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Pujadesibataller.2007">
                <label>Pujades i Bataller 2007</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author"><name>
                            <surname>Pujades i Bataller</surname>
                            <given-names>Ramon Josep</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Les cartes portolanes: La representació medieval d’una mar
                        solcada</article-title>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="Ralle.2014">
                <label>Ralle 2014</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name>
                            <surname>Ralle</surname>
                            <given-names>Inga</given-names>
                        </name></person-group>
                    <year>2014</year>
                    <article-title>Selbstzeugnisse der Frühen Neuzeit in der Herzog August
                        Bibliothek: Digitale Edition des Diariums von Herzog August dem
                        Jüngeren</article-title>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15499/edoc/ed000225</pub-id>
                    <uri xlink:href="http://selbstzeugnisse.hab.de/edition/diarium/1600"
                        >http://selbstzeugnisse.hab.de/edition/diarium/1600</uri>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>

        </ref-list>
        <fn-group content-type="footnotes">
            <title>Footnotes</title>
            <fn id="omc47vnulsv">
                <label>1</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="zau1nngk39qa">
                <label>2</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Guckelsberger.2022">(Guckelsberger/Geus
                    2022)</xref></p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
                <label>3</label>
                <p>A notable exception is <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Harvey.1991">(Harvey 1991,
                        77)</xref>, which shows a slither of the map around the Venetian Lagoon and
                    the Po Delta. Milanesi gives the few available citations prior to 2006, see
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008)</xref>,
                    specifically note 3 there. Since 2009, a few remarks have been included in some
                    book publications referring to Milanesi’s text, but a thorough discussion or
                    analysis has yet to come to my attention.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
                <label>4</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Grenacher.1948">(Grenacher 1948)</xref>. It reports
                    the few facts known about its provenance and is accessible online, URL:<ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5169/seals-323083"
                        >http://doi.org/10.5169/seals-323083</ext-link> (accessed 15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
                <label>5</label>
                <p>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2022">(Milanesi 2022)</xref>, preprint
                    available through personal communication with author in 2019. Milanesi also
                    shows that Biondo depends on Cotton-like maps and not the other way round
                    because he ignores some other Alpine rivers which are presented in great detail
                    on the Cotton.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
                <label>6</label>
                <p>The corresponding cartometric enquiry is vast and thus outside the scope of the
                    present publication. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="k0ujxfn3kh9m">fig.
                        8</xref> in this article.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
                <label>7</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Meurer.1999">(Meurer 1999)</xref>. URL: <ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/pnd100955037.html#ndbcontent"
                        >https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/pnd100955037.html#ndbcontent</ext-link>
                    (accessed 15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
                <label>8</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Harvey.1987">(Harvey 1987, 464)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="rflxrxtcellu">
                <label>9</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Harvey.1987">(Harvey 1987, 498)</xref> appendix
                    20.1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="a6jhs3mdko4h">
                <label>10</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Harvey.1987">(Harvey 1987, 481)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="zdm1u14t6vci">
                <label>11</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008, 153)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="vl8u5xiba41">
                <label>12</label>
                <p>See also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Cacheyjr.2018">(Cachey Jr. 2018)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
                <label>13</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Campbell.2011">(Campbell 2011)</xref>, URL: <ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://www.maphistory.info/portolancensus.html"
                        >https://www.maphistory.info/portolancensus.html</ext-link> (accessed
                    09.09.2017).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
                <label>14</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="lilley">(Lilley/Millea/Vetch)</xref>, <ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.goughmap.org/about/"
                        >http://www.goughmap.org/about/</ext-link> (accessed 15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
                <label>15</label>
                <p>A compilation of such maps was published in the 1950s, see <xref ref-type="bibr"
                        rid="BennetDurand.1952">(Bennet Durand 1952)</xref>. By the 1990s, however,
                    this designation as a ‘corpus’ was shown to be meaningless, see <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Dalche.1996">(Dalché 1996)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
                <label>16</label>
                <p>Why is Narnia a member of this illustrious assembly? Mapmakers are known to have
                    sometimes highlighted their home towns in a particular way. See, for instance,
                    the French scribe Hugo Comminelli (Hugues Commineau) and his illustrations in
                    the “Octavus et ultimus liber” of Claudius Ptolomaeus, Cosmographia, Jacobus
                    Angelus interpres, 1451–1500[?], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Commineau.1451"
                        >(Commineau 1451)</xref>. The online “Historique de la conservation” on this
                    object (Latin 4802) states: “Le copiste, originaire de Mézières sur la Meuse, a
                    indiqué sa ville natale au f. 126 en petites lettres noires: ‘Macerie supra
                    Mosa(m)’”, URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc63677b"
                        >https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc63677b</ext-link>
                    (accessed 15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
                <label>17</label>
                <p>Within a radius of 40 kilometers there are eight important towns in the region:
                    Salerno, Naples, Nola, Aversa, Castel Volturno, Capua, Benevento, and
                    Ariano-Irpino.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
                <label>18</label>
                <p>The distance and graphical representation of the network is solely based on the
                    identification of locations which I could identify along the rivers, not on
                    their course in the landscape.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
                <label>19</label>
                <p>On the central role of rivers as a reference grid for organizing urban space see,
                    for instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Dalche.2005">(Dalché 2005)</xref>. With
                    respect to the twelfth-century Expositio mappa mundi, he writes: “Il y a des
                    points fixes ou des lignes, par rapport auxquels les peuples et les cités sont
                    disposés. […] les réalités géographiques les plus importantes pour la
                    structuration de l’espace continental sont internes à celui-ci: ce sont les
                    fleuves.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
                <label>20</label>
                <p>At the moment of writing, not all of the tributaries to tributaries are
                    documented but the importance for mapmaking, organization of space, and the
                    impressively detailed knowledge displayed are sufficiently clear.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
                <label>21</label>
                <p>See the revealing chapter by Florian Mittenhuber on the catastrophic consequences
                    for the outline of the Mediterranean due to erroneous coordinates for Tunis,
                    Marseille, and Istanbul, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Mittenhuber.2009b"
                        >(Mittenhuber 2009)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
                <label>22</label>
                <p>In contrast to the stellar catalogues useful for astrology, Ptolemy’s Geography
                    was never really commented on or used before the 1460s. On its reception, see
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Mittenhuber.2009">(Mittenhuber/Klöti
                    2009)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
                <label>23</label>
                <p>Geodesically accurate to within 1 kilometer.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
                <label>24</label>
                <p>It is also missing from another “great map of Italy”, the anonymous map of 1449,
                    from Cicogna, preserved in Venice, at the Museo Correr, Dept. 19, <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
                <label>25</label>
                <p>Both the black-and-white format and the lower-resolution image of the Cotton as
                    compared to the Strasbourg diminish the visually pleasing rendering of the
                    Cotton, which assembles five buildings behind a wall.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
                <label>26</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008)</xref> writes in note
                    60 when describing the Cotton: “[...] Strasborgo, che le assomiglia tanto da
                    sembrarne una brutta copia, o una parente povera.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
                <label>27</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Pujadesibataller.2007">(Pujades i Bataller 2007,
                        199)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
                <label>28</label>
                <p>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Campbell.2013">(Campbell 2013)</xref>, URL:<ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="http://www.maphistory.info/RedNamesCommentary.html"
                        >http://www.maphistory.info/RedNamesCommentary.html </ext-link>(accessed
                    11.10.2019).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="irrryp9si628">
                <label>29</label>
                <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Grenacher.1948">(Grenacher 1948,
                        18)</xref>, the Strasbourg was first presented at the Seventh International
                    Congress of Historical Sciences that took place in Warsaw in 1933.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
                <label>30</label>
                <p>Witte was the first philological editor of the Divine Comedy. His very rich
                    collection on Dante’s writings was acquired by the Universitäts- und
                    Landesbibliothek in the then-German Strasbourg in 1883, but was lost after 1918,
                    it seems along with the map. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Briguglia.2017">(See
                        Briguglia 2017)</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://www.ilpost.it/gianlucabriguglia/2017/04/10/dante-a-strasburgo/"
                        >link</ext-link> accessed 11.10.2019): “After the construction of the
                    National and University Library, a great appeal was made to the Germanic world
                    for donations of library funds, collections, books, manuscripts, and the Kaiser
                    himself invested a great deal in acquiring as much as possible. This is how the
                    library came into possession […] of the legacy of Karl Witte, which was sold in
                    1883.” (My translation of: “dopo la costruzione della Biblioteca nazionale e
                    dell’università, si lanciò un grande appello al mondo germanico a donazioni di
                    fondi librari, di collezioni, di libri, di manoscritti, e il Kaiser stesso
                    investì moltissimo nell’acquisizione di quanto più fosse possibile. È così che
                    la Biblioteca venne in possesso [...] del patrimonio di Karl Witte, che fu
                    ceduto nel 1883.”)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
                <label>31</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008)</xref> only quotes
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Almagia.1929">(Almagià 1929, 8)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="j51g24n2vv6a">
                <label>32</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Grenacher.1948">(Grenacher 1948)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
                <label>33</label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Domenico.2002">(Domenico 2002, 205)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
                <label>34</label>
                <p>By their very nature, the statistical numbers of course come with substantial
                    uncertainties. It is thus reasonable to argue in rounded numbers.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
                <label>35</label>
                <p>Unfortunately, the counterpart to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmflhjs942df">fig.
                        5</xref> on the Tyrrhenian coast does not display a similarly distinctive
                    break in scale, mostly due to a lack of named vignettes, possibly because the
                    scribe had problems matching inconsistent information in the overlapping
                    region.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
                <label>36</label>
                <p>Considerable scholarly effort is currently being made to better understand the
                    emergence of portolan charts. For the general context, see <xref ref-type="bibr"
                        rid="Edson.2007">(Edson 2007, 37)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
                <label>37</label>
                <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008,
                        172)</xref>, the text “De origine urbium Italie” on the Cotton proposes
                    that: “Rome is but an episode, and not the principal, in the history of Italy;
                    and the other cities, so important in the philo-Venetian <italic>De origine
                        urbium Italie</italic>, literally disappear: the history of Italy is made
                    complete with the foundation of Venice.” (My translation of: “Roma non e che un
                    episodio, e non il principale, della storia d’Italia; e le altre citta, cosi
                    importanti nel pur filoveneziano <italic>De origine urbium Italie</italic>,
                    letteralmente scompaiono: la storia dell’Italia si compie con la fondazione di
                    Venezia.”)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
                <label>38</label>
                <p>For example, this is indeed the case for Scotland on the Gough Map. It is
                    depicted on a perceptibly smaller scale than England.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
                <label>39</label>
                <p>The 38 maps in the Cortona Atlas appear as an exception. To quote Tony Campbell
                    in his entry “Anonymous Works and the Question of Their Attribution to
                    Individual Chartmakers or to Their Supposed Workshops”, on Map History/History
                    of Cartography (March 2011): “Because the traditional (i.e., Mediterranean and
                    Black Sea) charts in this ‘atlas’ – which is actually much more than that,
                    comprising also a merchant’s and navigator’s compendium – were evidently copied
                    from archival copies in some Venetian repository around 1489,” <xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Campbell.2011">(Campbell 2011)</xref> (<ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="http://www.maphistory.info/PortolanAttributions.html#cornaro"
                        >link</ext-link> accessed: 23.10.2019).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
                <label>40</label>
                <p>My translation of Milanesi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi
                        2008, 164)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
                <label>41</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Mesenburg.1986">(Mesenburg 1986)</xref>. Mesenburg
                    here presents a portolan chart by Ben Zar from 1497 which gave a radius of 327.5
                    ± 3.6 millimeters. See also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Mesenburg.1990"
                        >(Mesenburg 1990)</xref>, for the portolan chart of Petrus Roselli of 1449,
                    which gave a radius of 257.7 ± 1.1 millimeters. These were the first and
                    fundamental studies: the reference points for calibration were the sixteen tiny
                    compass holes and their corresponding wind roses on the perimeter that were
                    visible on the verso. In both cases, shrinkage was more pronounced head to tail
                    (meaning east to west), compared to the direction perpendicular to it, ‘belly to
                    belly’ (that is, north to south). This fact was confirmed in personal
                    communication with the author in 2020.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
                <label>42</label>
                <p>Within the present investigation concerning Biondo’s source maps, this is not an
                    option.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
                <label>43</label>
                <p>Details will be presented in a forthcoming cartometric study. Several tears,
                    expertly repaired, have resulted in jumps in the grid lines at several places
                    not documented in the above survey which only uses coordinates spaced five
                    centimeters apart, as indicated by the dots.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
                <label>44</label>
                <p>I did this mathematically by rotating 96 Strasbourg coordinates against the
                    Cotton coordinates around the point (x=0,y=0) of the Cotton and minimizing the
                    root mean square error along the common coastal stretches in both seas. The
                    minimum was well defined as 1.3 centimeters at 3 ± 0.25 degrees. The best fit is
                    shown above for the whole outlines.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
                <label>45</label>
                <p>In the present context, the only significant mention of Albenga that I could find
                    is its mention in the <italic>Liber de Existencia Riveriarum et Forma Maris
                        Nostri Mediterranei</italic>, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Dalche.1995"
                        >(Dalché 1995)</xref>, line 1804.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
                <label>46</label>
                <p>The Cotton mentions a “geloran” at this location on the map. Campbell’s list of
                    portolan sites <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Campbell.2011">(Campbell 2011)</xref>
                    has no mention of a “guloran” or “geloran” but lists Capo Linaro at modern-day
                    Santa Marinella, which would indeed serve as the logical possible ‘next stop’
                    for seafarers after Fiumcino, but poses a wide linguistic gap in change of
                    name.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
                <label>47</label>
                <p>Due to the bad state of preservation of the Strasbourg map, in a number of cases
                    identification is subjective.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="tvsd9r1zwrib">
                <label>48</label>
                <p>A travel diary of 1600 of August the Younger, duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg, reads:
                    “den 28 Augusti ♃, Laviso dorf, Bressano dorf, La rave dorf, Castell Königsperg,
                    Castell salorno mitten dorf, Newmarckt flecken zur kronen, 4 meill, biß Brunzuol
                    dorf, Leyfers dorf, Botzen flecken zum Cardinalßhuett 3 meill, facit 7.” A
                    transcript is viewable online, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Ralle.2014">(Ralle
                        2014)</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="http://selbstzeugnisse.hab.de/edition/diarium/1600"
                        >link</ext-link> accessed 03.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="uahbh522xhfm">
                <label>49</label>
                <p>Better images and visual inspection of the original may clarify some of the
                    remaining issues.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="i7tp6qqyvn0g">
                <label>50</label>
                <p>According to Luca Melchior: “[...] the historical Friuli are devoid of physical
                    boundaries – hydrographic or orographic – that separate them clearly from the
                    surrounding areas. However, if the southern border were the Adriatic Sea, then
                    the ‘natural’ borders of the Friuli territory can be considered the River Isonzo
                    to the east and the River Livenza to the west – while the territories to the
                    left of the southern half of this are found, however, in the administrative
                    region of Veneto.” (My translation of: “Considerando il cosiddetto Friuli
                    storico, questo risulta privo di confini fisici – idrografici o orografici – che
                    lo separino nettamente dalle regioni circonvicine. Tuttavia, se a sud il confine
                    è costituito dal mar Adriatico, i confini ‘naturali’ del territorio friulano
                    possono essere considerati a est il fiume Isonzo, a ovest il fiume Livenza – i
                    territori a sinistra della metà meridionale di questo si trovano tuttavia, nella
                    regione amministrativa del Veneto.”) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Melchior.2018"
                        >(Melchior 2018)</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="http://www.kit.gwi.uni-muenchen.de/?p=13160#26v=1"
                        >link</ext-link> accessed 16.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kinxkucfdme">
                <label>51</label>
                <p>Many subsequent cartographers retained the source lake of the River Po, from
                    Donnus Nicolaus Germanus’s Sexta Europa Tabula in the Ulm edition of Ptolemy of
                    1482, to Waldseemüller’s Tabula Moderna of 1513 (with an enormous lake), and
                    Sebastian Munster’s Italia XIX Nova Tabula in his <italic>Cosmographia</italic>
                    of 1545.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
                <label>52</label>
                <p>For an overview see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Harvey.1980">(Harvey
                    1980)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
                <label>53</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008, 164)</xref>, writes:
                    “The rendering of the Adriatic and Tuscan wetlands and the lakes of northern
                    Lazio is equally meticulous; the basins of the Arno and Tiber are well designed
                    and in the right proportions, even if the caesura between coast and interior is
                    made evident by the course of the Tiber, which in Tuscia runs too close to the
                    coast. The design of Tuscany precedes that of Pietro del Massaio (1459), which,
                    however, does not differ much, even in the fluid style of representation;
                    however, the Ombrone Basin is missing, as in the Correr map, and the
                    distribution of the centers of southern Tuscany is affected; La Chiana is also
                    confused with Paglia, while the marshes of the Chiana and the Castiglione Lake
                    (~Maremma) are well represented.” (My translation of: “La resa delle paludi
                    adriatiche e toscane, e dei laghi del Lazio settentrionale, è altrettanto
                    minuziosa; i bacini dell’Arno e del Tevere sono ben disegnati e nelle giuste
                    proporzioni, anche se la cesura tra costa e interno è resa evidente dal corso
                    del Tevere, che nella Tuscia corre troppo vicino alla costa. Il disegno della
                    Toscana precede quello di Pietro del Massaio [1459], che per altro non se ne
                    discosta molto, anche nello stile fluido dela rappresentazione; manca tuttavia
                    il bacino dell’Ombrone, come nella carta del Correr, e la distribuzione dei
                    centri della Toscana meridionale ne risente; la Chiana è inoltre confusa col
                    Paglia, mentre sono ben rappresentati le paludi della Chiana e il Lago di
                    Castiglione.”)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
                <label>54</label>
                <p>“Lago d’ prusia” in the upper-left corner of the image.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
                <label>55</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2005b">(Biondo 2005b, 313)</xref>: “The Padusan
                    marsh begins at the canal, according to the geographers the only marsh in Italy.
                    Vergil says of it in the Georgics: ‘or the stream of Padusa teeming with fish.’
                    The term embraces all the lagoons, swamps and marshes that we see lying between
                    the Po and the territory of Flaminia (or Emilia) [...].”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
                <label>56</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Biondo.2016">(Biondo 2016, 72)</xref>, note 55:
                    “Venetias [...] Habet autem eius ducatus regio longitudinem milium octoginta
                    [...] Latitudo autem varia nullos habet alios terminos quam quousque cedentes
                    recedentesque mans aquae ad siccum stanando perveniunt.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
                <label>57</label>
                <p>The remnants are now known as the “Padule di Fucecchio”.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
                <label>58</label>
                <p>My translation of [Anon.]: “Le colline del Chiuso (tra Cortona, Valiano e
                    Foiano), per la posizione strategica, erano in antico munite di castelli e
                    dotate, sebbene rudimentalmente, di porti per l’ approdo di barche in servizio
                    sulla Chiana. Rimane oggi la denominazione de ‘Il porto’ a Farneta, a Cignano,
                    Fasciano, Bettolle, Creti, Foiano e Cesa. Il porto di Farneta è dirimpettaio del
                    Porto di Foiano della Chiana […]”, from “Gli interventi medievali e la
                    situazione antecedente all’ egemonia medicea sulla Toscana”, URL: <ext-link
                        ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="http://www.valdichiana.it/bonifica/storia2.php"
                        >http://www.valdichiana.it/bonifica/storia2.php</ext-link> (accessed
                    15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
                <label>59</label>
                <p>Similarly, Guelph Grosseto was contested by Siena until 1336.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
                <label>60</label>
                <p>Warfare may also have hindered amelioration, the improvement of agricultural land
                    by draining.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
                <label>61</label>
                <p>From the image with the highest resolution I could find in the public domain, in
                    this case the Cosmographia Claudii Ptolomaei Alexandrini Mathematicorum
                    Principis [...], 1467, Biblioteka Ordynacji Zamojskiej w Warszawie, Rps BOZ 2,
                    URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://polona.pl/item/cosmographia-claudii-ptolomaei-alexandrini-mathematicorum-principis-seculo-secundo,NzQ1NjM4Ng/18/#info:metadata"
                        >https://polona.pl/item/cosmographia-claudii-ptolomaei-alexandrini-mathematicorum-principis-seculo-secundo,NzQ1NjM4Ng/18/#info:metadata</ext-link>
                    (accessed 15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
                <label>62</label>
                <p>See, for example, image of acc. no. RCIN 912278 in the Royal Collection, URL:
                        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://www.rct.uk/collection/912278/a-map-of-the-valdichiana"
                        >https://www.rct.uk/collection/912278/a-map-of-the-valdichiana</ext-link>
                    (accessed 15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
                <label>63</label>
                <p>Similar observations are seen in the lake district of northern Italy: in reality
                    the Ticino issues into Lago Maggiore at a point between Ascona and Locarno but
                    both maps show it flowing into the lake at a spot east of Locarno. Also, Lake
                    Varese is missing on both maps, as is the Ombrone river in Tuscany.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
                <label>64</label>
                <p>Above sea level.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
                <label>65</label>
                <p>In measuring, I have used the lower central point of the relevant large vignettes
                    on the Cotton. These usually feature a black portcullis which is easily spotted,
                    especially in faded areas. Most vignettes on the Strasbourg are so tiny that
                    they pose no problem when measuring the distance between two points.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn66">
                <label>66</label>
                <p>A typical example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="igq5jgxi81q4">fig. 10</xref> is
                    “mazasco”/Massasco above Sestri Levante at the confluence of the River Torrente
                    Petronio and a small stream. The vignette above that, “matalana”/Mattarano is
                    correctly placed in the Strasbourg at the headwaters of the Petronio. In the
                    Cotton, although at a similar place, its orientation suggests a very different
                    location up-stream on the small stream. One may take this as an indication that
                    the definitive placement and/or orientation of the vignette was left to the
                    miniaturist of the map. This is also suggested by fairly frequent left
                    bank/right bank switches, resulting from restricted space or aesthetic concerns.
                    It is worth remembering that the map is extremely crowded, especially in the
                    Levante, compared to the conventional density of features on modern maps.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
                <label>67</label>
                <p>Not only vignettes but also estuaries and confluences furnish additional
                    geographical information which also figures frequently in Biondo’s text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
                <label>68</label>
                <p>The remote but disputed Alpine valleys are rendered in superb detail.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="vk9b01zupo9">
                <label>69</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008, 164)</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn70">
                <label>70</label>
                <p>A number of unreadable entries may or may not increase these numbers.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn71">
                <label>71</label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="Milanesi.2008">(Milanesi 2008, 156)</xref>. “Molly
                    Bourne, nel 1999, avanzava velatamente l’ipotesi che una di queste carte, la
                    Cotton, sia in qualche modo da mettere in rapporto con la carta murale
                    dell’Italia disegnata per la seconda volta da Antonio Leonardi in palazzo Ducale
                    a Venezia dopo l’incendio del 1483<sup>21</sup>”, (her) note 21: "<xref
                        ref-type="bibr" rid="Bourne.1999">(Bourne 1999, 65)</xref>. Peter Barber
                    (comunicazione personale) ritiene che le due carte possano avere avuto, quanto
                    meno, una fonte comune; il che mi sembra più che possibile.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn72">
                <label>72</label>
                <p>Paulini Minoritae de Venetiis opera historica, fol. 267v and 268r, known as Vat.
                    Lat. 1960 and available in high resolution from DigiVatLib, the Vatican
                    Library’s digitized collections, URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                        xlink:href="https://digi.vatlib.it/view/MSS_Vat.lat.1960"
                        >https://digi.vatlib.it/view/MSS_Vat.lat.1960</ext-link> (accessed
                    15.07.2020).</p>
            </fn>
        </fn-group>
    </back>
</article>
